<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Making the Case for GHG Reductions | Climate Change</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Making the Case for GHG Reductions | Climate Change</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-08-01 14:14:15.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://climatechange.foreignpolicyblogs.com/2010/02/04/making-the-case-for-ghg-reductions/</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>amanda little</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>institute for public policy research</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>john kerry</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>lindsey graham</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>nancy pelosi</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>waxman-markey</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/ENV_EN/10572.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Thursday, February 4 2:16 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p2">I had a good time the other night talking about climate change policy and politics with Amanda Little on The Hyperbole Hour . We’re on the same wavelength. (You can download the show as an mp3 file and listen in from around 29 minutes.)</p>
			<p id="p3">One of the points we made was that we really need to sell the case in the US for why cap-and-trade and clean tech are the only way to fly. In response to an FT analysis on Copenhagen I noted the other day, there was a good letter that reinforces this point from two worthies at the UK’s Institute for Public Policy Research . They say “…the politics of climate change are tough.” (That’s an understatement.) They go on to note “This calls for an urgent reframing of the issue in terms that matter to people now: less dependence on oil, investment in renewable energy, renewed economic growth as a result of innovation, jobs, and security.” That’s all true.</p>
			<p id="p4">Beyond that, there are the costs involved in ignoring the issue. How is it possible for the elected representatives of people in the Gulf Coast and Texas, in the wake of Hurricanes Katrina and Ike, or for that matter, representatives from farm states, who are going to be crushed by warming, to vote against Waxman-Markey ? It’s possible because we’re not yet making the case convincing enough, particularly in the face of dogmatic opposition by some as well as subterfuge from special interests.</p>
			<p id="p5">Andrew Leonard notes one lonely Republican voice in the Senate, Lindsey Graham. Graham is even pushing back on President Obama’s recent display of reticence on bringing cap-and-trade forward this year. Graham’s remarks , courtesy of Grist, indicate some fight that may be lacking among the Democratic caucus in the Senate and at the White House. “You don’t have to believe that Iowa is going to become beachfront property to want to clean up carbon,” says Graham. “It is not about polar bears to me, it’s about jobs. I like the polar bears as much as anyone else but I want to create jobs.”</p>
			<p id="p6">Why aren’t Barack Obama, John Kerry, Nancy Pelosi, and the truly sterling Obama cabinet appointees blistering the airwaves and the hustings with this message?</p>
			<p id="p7">5 Comments So Far»</p>
			<p id="p8">Windy City Kid on 10/02/2010 in 14:57 </p>
			<p id="p9">Hello Bill! You may be unaware but the weather in the Midwest has been similar to that of the 1800s for the last two years and harvests are down significantly because of the cold. We’ve had snow on the ground for 2 months and people aren’t thinking about the consequences of global warming.</p>
			<p id="p10">Job approval for those listed in your article is on the decline, and political capital, unlike paper money, is a finite commodity which few politicians will use on cap and trade in order to be reelected. Campaigning has begun for the November elections and climate change, by most polling, has become one of the lowest priorities for voters in this struggling economy.</p>
			<p id="p11">Then there is the economic impact of W-M, as outlined by the EIA and CBO, of .25% to .75% decline in GDP through 2020 and a net loss of jobs overall with implementation of W-M.</p>
			<p id="p12">W-M cap and trade is viewed as ineffective by many supporters of Dr. James Hansen who regards cap and trade as symbolism over substance and which does nothing but enrich Goldman Sachs and Wall Street millionaires. Given the ugly truth about the carbon trading market in Europe being controlled by the underworld, no one trusts the system anymore.</p>
			<p id="p13">I wish I was smart enough to suggest a solution that was win win for all Americans as I don’t really care about the corporations or the political class, but somehow even if I could I’m sure that it would be gutted in the political process. Dr. James Hansen has the best plan to build from IMO.</p>
			<p id="p14">Best Regards,</p>
			<p id="p15">Thanks for this, Kid. You are certainly preaching to the choir here when you assert that the politics of climate change legislation are difficult and dirty. I’ve written about that many times here. But what I’ve also been saying is that there are misperceptions by the bushel, owing to concerted efforts by some ideologues and special interests to sow confusion. It is the role of folks like me to try to undo some of those misperceptions. As to Jim Hansen , I have nothing but total respect for him as a climate scientist. Let’s just say our opinions diverge on policy.</p>
			<p id="p16">On impacts on the nation’s breadbasket, see this , for instance, from the National Academies. I also referenced a report here on why farmers should be terrified of the looming impacts and not be at all concerned about costs in mitigation and adaptation. The view on impacts is underscored by this comprehensive study by the US Dept. of Agriculture. “The report focuses on the next 25 to 50 years, and finds that climate change is already affecting U.S. water resources, agriculture, land resources, and biodiversity, and will continue to do so.” As to the costs to farmers from Waxman-Markey, Ag. also looked at that here . “In fact, the impact on net farm income is less than a 1% decrease. In the short run, agricultural offset markets may cover these costs. Over the medium-term and long-term, costs to agriculture rise but remain modest (3.5% and 7.2% decreases in net farm income, respectively). However, benefits to agriculture from an offsets market rise over time and will likely overtake costs in the medium and long term.”</p>
			<p id="p17">Windy City Kid on 10/02/2010 in 21:52 </p>
			<p id="p18">Bill, thanks for taking your valuable time to provide so much information. This is an area I need more education on and I look forward to reading the reports that you provided.</p>
			<p id="p19">Best Regards,</p>
			<p id="p20">The Pseudoscience of Global warming</p>
			<p id="p21">Many U.S. and International academic climatologist now agree, in whole or in part, that the sun causes a considerable amount, if not all, of the earth’s surface temperature variability and that C02 fluctuations follow this variability – not the reverse. The science behind this is reviewed briefly on the next two pages and is convincing. Most independent atmospheric scientists are on board. Government and U.N. supported departments are recalcitrant due to secure grant support and to avoid career embarrassment. The debate has become idealogical – similar to Darwinism in the late 19th century. The larger science community has been slower. Most have a vague understanding of black body radiation but evidence for C02 lagging temperature variability has only recently come to light. Also, the retrograde solubility of C02 has not yet been widely publicized. The public lags way behind as do many purveyors of the news—undoubtedly because C02 has been publicized in the same breath as “pollution”, “climate change”, and “global warming”. This makes for an easy villain in a simple story. This is clearly wrong!</p>
			<p id="p22">The primary mouthpiece of this pseudoscience is the IPCC—which was from the beginning, and still is, a political rather than a scientific entity sepp.org ). Each of 4 reports since 1990 has a Summary for Policymakers written by member governments and not by the scientists on whose work it is based. All 4 reports have drawn criticism from independent researchers for astounding misstatement of fact, omission of data, falsification of trends, faulty models, and exaggerated conclusions. 100 independent climatologists signed a Leipzig declaration against the IPCC in 1996. 1500 scientists signed an Oregon Institute petition against IPCC findings and recommendations in 1997. This number has now grown to more than 31,000 interested scientists osim.org ). Most original IPCC scientists have left their positions. Certain Journals have maintained their connections for financial reasons. Peer review is now only possible by certain selected peers. Certain papers are automatically accepted or turned down based on the authors’ known views on the subject. The naïve acceptance of such peer-reviewed literature by policymakers is a joke.</p>
			<p id="p23">On the other hand there are hundreds of reputable atmospheric scientists who know that solar cycles control most, if not all, of earth’s temperature variation. These include the late Dr. Frederick Seitz, Nat. Academy of Sciences; Dr. John Christie, Univ. of Alabama; Dr. Roger Pielke, Univ. of Colorado; Dr. Fred Singer, Univ. of Virginia; Dr. Patrick Michaels, George Mason Univ; Dr. Richard Lindzen, MIT; Dr. Ian Pilner, Univ. of Adelaide; Dr. Howard Hayden, Univ. of Connecticut; Lord Christopher Monckton, Scotland; Dr. Zbigniew Jaworowski, Poland; Dr. Bob Carter, Australia; Dr. Dick Thoenes, Eindhoven Univ; –and hundreds of others. In addition many organizations have been set up to relay truthful science to policymakers and the public including the Science and Public Policy Institute, The Center for Science and Public Policy, Friends of Science, and the Science and Environmental Policy Project. This latter group sepp.org ) and its sister organization- The Nongovernmental International Panel on Climate Change—published it’s 2008 report: “Nature, Not Human Activity, Rules the Climate” nipccreport.org ). It’s contributors are international unsponsored luminaries in the field and are only interested in disseminating true facts concerning climate variability and its causes.</p>
			<p id="p24">At this point true climate science needs to overcome more than unwieldy ice cores and conflicting surface temperature data sets. They are fighting well funded zealots and governments whose motives are idealogy rather than science. They are fighting a political machine including govt. sponsored websites, K-12 education programs, movies, books, and agency funded elaborate productions on the NGO channel. Prof. Howard Hayden has remarked about this “global warming pseudoscience”—-“What other basic scientific truth has ever needed $300 million to promote itself?” We even have a cabinet level Secretary of Climate Change!</p>
			<p id="p25">The problem is not science. The problem is getting the word out. The NIPCC 2008 report (above) is impressive but lengthy. My 2 page synopsis (below) will help. We need to educate as many policymakers and science commentators as possible in this remote area of C02 solubility and Solar System astronomy.</p>
			<p id="p26">Beside faulty chemistry and astronomy, and beyond incredibly misguided public policy—this “C02/ pollution/ global warming” pseudoscience may be the largest hoax ever foisted on the American people and the world. It ranks with “eugenics”— the pseudoscience disaster of the early 20th century. Public policy take note. Scientists take note. Unguarded science can morph into something quite different if you let it.</p>
			<p id="p27">You’ll learn from and enjoy this 3 minute exercise on temperature and C02.</p>
			<p id="p28">Robert G. Dillon, M.D.</p>
			<p id="p29">Strangely—little has been mentioned of the chemistry involving C02 and temperature:</p>
			<p id="p30">C02 + H20 H2C03 H+ + HC03- +(Ca)= CaC03+ H+</p>
			<p id="p31">This equation is a synopsis of C02 / ocean water chemistry. C02 has retrograde solubility- i.e.-more C02 is dissolved in water with a cooler temperature (4% more solubility per 1 degree C. fall in temp) therefore removing C02 from the atmosphere and forming bicarbonate ion and carbonate – and extending eventually to the formation of calcium carbonate rocks. . Heat shifts the equation to the left with gradual atmospheric C02 liberation with ocean warming. Atmospheric C02 concentration is primarily determined by temperature rather than the other way around. This is easily demonstrated in the laboratory and it has been shown to be the case in ice core samples on several continents that prehistoric atmospheric C02 concentration follows atmospheric temperature changes by several hundred years—not the reverse. This C02 variation is best seen in long 50,000-100,000 year glacial (cold) and interglacial (warm) periods. It is now seen in shorter cycles – years and decades – as discussed below. The main sink of atmospheric C02 is HC03- and dissolved C02 in the oceans which is 61 times atm.C02. The largest reservoir of C02 is CaC03 in carbonate rocks (limestone), dolomite, and calcites, etc. which is 141,000 times the amt of C02 in the atmosphere. This equation has been shifting left and right during short, medium and long solar cycles (warm and cold periods) for more than a billion years.</p>
			<p id="p32">Interestingly, C02 is a blessing. Lab studies show 50% faster growth of all plant species when grown in a 3X C02 environment (consider Cambrian and Jurassic below).</p>
			<p id="p33">Only .035% of the atmosphere is C02. Only 3% of this C02 comes from fossil fuels. This is 0.001% or 1/100,000 of all atmospheric molecules are anthropogenic C02. Consider this with the knowledge that C02 levels were 20X higher in the Cambrian period (550 million yrs. ago) when there was an explosion of plant and animal life. Even in the 200 million year ago Jurassic period C02 was 5X present levels. C02 decreased ~ 50 million years ago due to changes in outgasing from ocean ridges, volcanoes, and increased carbon burial. In the past 400,000 years C02 has varied between 180-380ppm. During this time lower C02 levels have tracked 100,000 yr. cold glaciations and higher C02 levels have followed warm interglacial periods. Interestingly, these glacial cycles coincide with the 100,000 year earth/sun orbital eccentricity cycles.</p>
			<p id="p34">Earth’s surface has probably cooled slightly the past 10 years. It probably warmed slightly from 1975-1998. It cooled from 1949-1975. It warmed from 1750-1940 after spending~400 years in the Little Ice Age. It cooled from the Medieval Warm period from 1000 AD - 1750 AD (LIAge). It really cooled from the Holocene Warm Maximum ~5000 BCE to any subsequent or present date. Any temperature prior to 11000 years ago was cooler than present due to the 90,000 year Wurm Glaciation, and there were dozens,perhaps hundreds, of these glaciations and interglacial warm peaks in the millions of years before that. There were at least 4 Snow Ball earths in the past 2 billion years.</p>
			<p id="p35">Whether we compare ice ages, millennia, centuries or our own experience with decades, years, months and days—our climate surface temperature varies - on longer time frames with the sun/earth obliquity, precession and eccentricity cycles and on shorter periods with sunspot/sun rotation cycles and water vapor cloud cover. Other solar influences include cosmic ray fluxes and UV absorption induced local climate reversals. Recent observations suggest even Mars has warmed over several decades. Our Sun clearly controls our surface temperature. Atmospheric C02 depends of this temperature variation—it does not cause it.</p>
			<p id="p36">Atmospheric C02 seems to have increased this century. Of course it has. The surface temperature has increased! This has been the warmest century in hundreds of years. It’s no coincidence that the sunspot cycle has been maximal this past century. It’s also no coincidence that we are finally coming out of the Little Ice Age (which had no sun spots).</p>
			<p id="p37">Few investigators have stressed the chemical dynamics of C02 solubility and bicarbonate dissociation that temperature drives one way of the other. Temp. drives C02 – not the reverse. Are IPCC climatologists aware of this formula? Is anyone aware of this science? Is public policy ignoring this relationship? Where are news sources and science editors when we need them?</p>
			<p id="p38">Robert G. Dillon, M.D.</p>
			<p id="p39">enclosures: next page</p>
			<p id="p40">1 –IPCC dissent: Global warming Petition Project – 31,000 scientists who oppose, in whole or in part, IPCC findings and conclusions. oism.org</p>
			<p id="p41">WEB: sourcewatch.org __global warming skeptics: contains hundreds of prominent atmospheric scientists who disagree in whole or in part with the IPCC. These include Dr. S. Fred Singer, Dr. Art Robinson, Dr. Frederick Seitz, Dr. Richard Lindzen. Included also are dozens of scientific organizations including: Advancement of Sound Science Coalition, Center for Science and Public Policy, Science and Environmental Policy Project. Friends of Science, National Resources Stewardship Project, International Climate Science Coalition, Cooler Head Coalition, Science and Environmental Policy Project, Nongovernmental International Panel on Climate Change.</p>
			<p id="p42">Helpful:</p>
			<p id="p43">Taylor Publishing, 2009.</p>
			<p id="p44">Ken Schatten, Director Solar Research, National Science Foundation, Oxford Univ.</p>
			<p id="p45">Press, 1997.</p>
			<p id="p46">Vales Lake Publishing, 2008.</p>
			<p id="p47">Model.gif</p>
			<p id="p48">html</p>
			<p id="p49">8-Carbon dioxide in the Atmosphere_Relationship with Oceanic Concentration, //en.</p>
			<p id="p50">Wikipedia/wild/Carbon_dioxide_in_Earth’s_atmosphere#Relationship_with_oceanic_</p>
			<p id="p51">concentration</p>
			<p id="p52">Recent Millennia, Cambridge Univ. Press, 1990.</p>
			<p id="p53">10-Michael Crichton, “Why Politicized Science is Dangerous” in State of Fear, pg 631-</p>
			<p id="p54">638, Harper Collins, 2004.</p>
			<p id="p55">12-“Nature, Not Human Activity, Rules the Climate” ed. Prof Fred Singer, sepp.org</p>
			<p id="p56">Publications/NIPCC</p>
			<p id="p57">astrophysics at Ga. State University Bio: Retired physician in Atlanta. Presently a post graduate student in astronomy and</p>
			<p id="p58">Thanks for this, but I’ve got to say the science - the kind that is done by real scientists, publishing in peer-reviewed journals, and reproduced over and over again - says, in a word, no, it’s not the sun. (Sorry to be so blunt.) This article from Skeptical Science breaks it down for you. Ralph J. Cicerone, Ph.D., President, National Academy of Sciences, summed it up in testimony before Congress : “One area of debate has been the extent to which variations in the Sun might contribute to recent observed warming trends. The Sun’s total brightness has been measured by a series of satellite-based instruments for more than two complete 11-year solar cycles. Recent analyses of these measurements argue against any detectable long-term trend in the observed brightness to date. Thus, it is difficult to conclude that the Sun has been responsible for the warming observed over the past 25 years.” (For more, refer to RealClimate here and here .)</p>
			<p id="p59">Leave Comments Below»</p>
			<p id="p60">*</p>
			<p id="p61">To prove you're a person (not a spam script), type the security word shown in the picture.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>