<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Climate Change - Part 31</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Climate Change - Part 31</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-07 19:28:19.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://climatechange.foreignpolicyblogs.com/page/31/</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/ENV_EN/12751.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Sunday, February 8 1:47 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p2">Change is what the Obama campaign was advertising. They won and I, for my part, am not complaining about false advertising. I’ve been raving here (and here , and here , among other places) about how the new administration is really rolling up its sleeves and getting down to cases on climate change, renewables, the green economy, etc. So is the new Congress, as I’ve also duly noted a fair number of times, including in the last two posts below.</p>
			<p id="p3">Friday’s “NY Times” had an article summarizing some of the salient differences between the Bush and Obama administrations on key environmental issues. On climate change, the article says that Bush promoted “…a series of mainly voluntary climate and energy initiatives intended to slow the release of such gases, with no commitment to binding reductions at home or abroad.</p>
			<p id="p4">“Mr. Obama has taken precisely the opposite track. He spoke late last month of the specter of ‘violent conflict, terrible storms, shrinking coastlines’ and other perils from unchecked warming, while pressing his vision of prosperity rebuilt around clean cars and pollution-free power from the wind and sun.”</p>
			<p id="p5">In another somewhat stunning indication of the change of direction, the “LA Times” reports that U.S. financing groups pledge change on climate policies . In 2002, Greenpeace, Friends of the Earth and four cities in the Western US brought suit against the Export-Import Bank and the Overseas Private Investment Corp. because they’d financed projects abroad that exacerbated global warming and thereby harmed the cities that joined the suit. The plaintiffs argued that the federal aid agencies had not subjected the projects to environmental review as they should have under the National Environmental Policy Act , the foundation of American environmental law.</p>
			<p id="p6">After seven years, the agencies and the plaintiffs settled the suit. According to this release from Friends of the Earth, “…the Export-Import Bank will begin taking carbon dioxide emissions into account in evaluating fossil fuel projects and create an organization-wide carbon policy. The Overseas Private Investment Corporation will establish a goal of reducing greenhouse gas emissions associated with projects by 20 percent over the next ten years. Both agencies will commit to increasing financing for renewable energy.” For much more on the lawsuit, see this .</p>
			<p id="p7">Coincidence that the suit was settled less than a month into the new administration?</p>
			<p id="p8">Here’s another significant example of Obama and Co. switching things up: EPA drops appeal over utility mercury ruling . The Bush EPA had contested “…a ruling by a U.S. appeals court that the EPA violated the Clean Air Act in 2005 when it exempted coal plants from the strictest emission controls for mercury and other toxic substances like arsenic, lead and nickel.” The utility industry is keeping their appeal active and the Supreme Court will consider it on February 20. According to this Reuters story, “The nation’s 1,100 coal-burning units emit about 48 tons of mercury each year, the largest unregulated U.S. source.”</p>
			<p id="p9">Mercury? So what? See this report from the consortium of Northeast US states fighting air pollution. Do you eat fish? You probably know then about the dangers of mercury. If not, see this report from NRDC.”</p>
			<p id="p10">Senate Environment and Public Works Committee Chair Barbara Boxer had a press conference earlier this week, as I noted under Keeping Up the Pace in the post just below. I watched some of it today on C-Span while I was having lunch. In the press conference, Boxer, along with Democratic colleagues from the committee, outlined what the principles are going to be for climate change legislation.</p>
			<p id="p11">Amy Klobuchar from Minnesota mentioned that the energy technology revolution is going to be very different from the information technology revolution in that the jobs are going to be available at different education levels, not just for folks with graduate degrees in computer science, and throughout the country, not just for people in Silicon Valley and other IT hotspots. (Go to minute 47:00 in the webcast.) Boxer further illustrated the importance of green jobs with examples of how California's requirements for energy efficiency and renewables are helping to bring some relief to the dire employment situation there.</p>
			<p id="p12">New Senator Jeff Merkeley of Oregon said VC, research institutes, and many others are waiting for a price on carbon that will pull them into the market. (Go to 48:45 at the webcast.) This precisely echoes the underlying sentiment of Fred Krupp and Miriam Horn's "Earth: The Sequel" : Innovation will flourish in response to economic incentives. See also Merkeley's release this week on green jobs and investment. He says, regarding the economic stimulus package before Congress, "This bill creates jobs now and lays the foundation to once again harness America's innovative know-how and lead the world in development and production of exciting new technologies. I'm especially pleased this bill focuses so much attention on capturing the new economic opportunities of green energy."</p>
			<p id="p13">Finally, Boxer was asked about Cap-and-Trade vs. Carbon Tax and said, unequivocally, it's going to be cap-and-trade. Why? Because Europe and others are already doing it, the Western States and the Northeast are doing it, Obama has said that's the way to proceed, and she wants legislation to be consonant with what the rest of the world is doing. She further noted the successes that cap-and-trade produced on acid rain here in the US.</p>
			<p id="p14">Here's what I wrote at this post nearly two years ago on that score:</p>
			<p id="p15">One of the progenitors of the "cap-and-trade" system that allows polluters to accumulate "credits" is Environmental Defense, back when they were the Environmental Defense Fund. The system was conceived with sulfur dioxide in mind. Acid rain is largely a consequence of sulfur dioxide emissions from electrical and industrial power plants. The push for this system to be deployed within the acid rain title of the Clean Air Act reauthorization was led by EDF. See " The Cap and Trade Success Story " from Environmental Defense. Very interestingly to me, at yesterday's symposium, Peter Koster, CEO of the European Climate Exchange , said that after Kyoto when the Europeans were looking for compliance mechanisms, they were urged by Clinton and Gore to adopt a "cap-and-trade" system because of the success of the acid rain program in the U.S.</p>
			<p id="p16">[Note: The FPA has upgraded its blog software and the font is going to be this one from here on out for my posts. We'll no doubt get used to it quickly.] </p>
			<p id="p17">Wednesday, February 4 1:48 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p18">No, we’re not Microsoft, but I’ve got some news you should be getting, if not critical software updates.</p>
			<p id="p19">Smart Grid - Smart idea for US energy policy is the title of the recent editorial from the “FT.” They say that the smart grid “would be a national asset comparable to the interstate highways launched by President Dwight D. Eisenhower in the 1950s.” They note that the new US Secretary of Energy, Steven Chu , is one of the strongest supporters of building out the smart grid. The excellent “Smart Grid News” has a story here about the economic stimulus package wending its way through the legislative process in Washington.</p>
			<p id="p20">When I wrote an article, Current Concerns , about the smart grid for “Planning,” I highlighted the work of Xcel Energy and Boulder. Here’s a recent TV segment from “NY1 News” on an integral component of the smart grid in Boulder , the smart house.</p>
			<p id="p21">Keeping Up the Pace - I’ve noted here that the new Obama administration is getting out of the starting blocks fast on climate change and energy. (See Hitting the Ground Running and Hitting the Ground Running - Part Deux .) Now Barbara Boxer, chair of the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee, has announced that her committee is going to be moving quickly to create a cap-and-trade system. See this from the “Washington Post” today and this from “The Hill.” The latter reports on Boxer’s statement of principles:</p>
			<p id="p22">Reduce emissions to levels guided by science to avoid dangerous global warming;</p>
			<p id="p23">Set short- and long-term emissions targets that are certain and enforceable;</p>
			<p id="p24">Use carbon market revenues to “keep consumers whole” and invest in clean-energy technologies and energy-efficiency measures.</p>
			<p id="p25">The other key Congressional entity for climate change legislation is the House Energy and Commerce Committee. The new chair, Henry Waxman , announced his intention a few weeks ago to move “quickly and decisively.” See Waxman promises quick action on climate change from the AP via “USA Today.” Waxman held hearings last month and took testimony from a number of the nation’s leading environmentalists and business leaders, all members of the US Climate Action Partnership . USCAP has called on Washington ” to quickly enact strong national legislation to require significant reductions of greenhouse gas emissions.”</p>
			<p id="p26">The Regulatory Track - It’s really up to the Congress and the President to come together on a portfolio of energy and climate laws that will change the trajectory toward catastrophe that we’re on now. But there are also measures that the new administration can take administratively. For one thing, as you already know, the EPA can allow states like California to pursue aggressive action. (See this from the blog last week.)</p>
			<p id="p27">A recent editorial from the “NY Times” suggest that the Obama administration take The Next Step on Warming . “The logical next step would be for Mr. Obama to quickly address the Supreme Court’s 2007 decision ordering the Environmental Protection Agency to examine the effects of greenhouse gases and to regulate them if necessary.” (See this on that critical decision from April 2007.) For her part, new EPA Administrator Lisa Jackson is unequivocal. In a recent memo to EPA employees, she said: “EPA will stand ready to help Congress craft strong, science-based climate legislation that fulfills the vision of the President. As Congress does its work, we will move ahead to comply with the Supreme Court’s decision recognizing EPA’s obligation to address climate change under the Clean Air Act.” You go, girl!</p>
			<p id="p28">The thoughtful David Roberts had this piece, The fierce urgency of now , at the nearly perfect “Gristmill” in December. In it he offers “some thoughts on the merits of regulating greenhouse gases via the Clean Air Act.” Check it out if you are a wonk or a WIT.</p>
			<p id="p29">Efficiency - We have looked at the marvels of energy efficiency a number of times, most recently here under Less is More. Take a look at these letters to the editor in response to another recent “NYT” editorial. Bottom line, as Tom Casten ( super genius ) notes: “Policies to induce the capture of wasted energy could profitably cut carbon dioxide emissions by 20 percent and greatly enhance manufacturing competitiveness.”</p>
			<p id="p30">My dictionary defines vector as “an organism (as an insect) that transmits a pathogen.”</p>
			<p id="p31">Researchers from Australia and the University of Wisconsin-Madison (my alma mater) have been looking at the species of mosquito that carries dengue fever. Their studies indicate that climate change, on its present track, will increase mosquito habitat across much of Australia, thus endangering many more millions of people than are now threatened. This, obviously, has implications for the whole world, not just Australia. See this map from the CDC.</p>
			<p id="p32">The World Health Organization is acutely aware of the mounting dangers involved. Their webpage devoted to climate change reflects a lot of research and fieldwork that’s being done to minimize the health impacts, including using climate to predict infectious disease epidemics .</p>
			<p id="p33">We’ve been reading Betsy Kolbert’s magisterial Field Notes from a Catastrophe in my class and I am reminded of the chapter, “The Butterfly and the Toad” about the changes in range and timing of many species, the potential for extinctions and the massive attenuation of ecosystem services .</p>
			<p id="p34">One of Kolbert’s subjects is a biologist at the University of York, Chris Thomas. He is involved in important new research that’s just been released on the global impact of climate change on biodiversity . Moths in Borneo, first studied in 1965, have been since shown to have “moved uphill by about 67 metres over the intervening years to cope with changes in climate.” As Thomas explains: “As these species get pushed uphill towards cooler conditions, the amount of land that is available to them gets smaller and smaller. And because most of the top of the mountain is bare rock, they may not be able to find suitable habitats, even if the temperature is right. Some of the species are likely to die out.”</p>
			<p id="p35">Climate change might also have some benefits in this context. One new study details the potential for the retreat of some invasive plant species in the western United States. One of the researchers is Michael Oppenheimer, the co-curator of the climate change exhibit at the American Museum of Natural History and a leading scientist and activist on climate change for many years. This article from Seedquest, who provide “global information services for seed professionals,” quote the authors: “Just as native species are expected to shift in range and relative competitiveness with climate change, the same should be expected of invasive species.” This provides an opportunity for the restoration of native species that have been crowded out over time by the invasives.</p>
			<p id="p36">It’s a consolation, certainly, but the threats from business as usual, as these authors well know, far outweigh the opportunities.</p>
			<p id="p37">Wednesday, January 28 12:48 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p38">The 27-nation European Union has come up with its proposals for how to proceed after the Kyoto Protocol expires in 2012. As you know, the world is going to sit down in Copenhagen in December and finalize an agreement. (See Further Thoughts on Poznan here from December.)</p>
			<p id="p39">EurActiv reports here that “According to the Commission, all developing countries except for the poorest ones should commit to adopting low-carbon development strategies by the end of 2011.” It further reports that “The EU executive will also urge developed countries to increase emission reduction commitments, opting for a binding agreement which would include all OECD member countries and all present and future EU member states.” The rapidly industrializing countries of Brazil, China, India, Indonesia and South Africa are very engaged with the OECD now and may well be on track to membership. Will the Copenhagen accord bind them in the end to firm numbers on GHG reductions? That’s one very big question.</p>
			<p id="p40">The European Commission published their paper today. The EU has its offer on the table. The Europeans have been in the lead. Last month, I reported on the EU’s own package: “Europe has passed its credibility test.” For more on what the EU is doing, see this excellent summary from the BBC.</p>
			<p id="p41">It’s up to the US now to take the ball and advance it. Given any number of indications from the new Obama administration , as discussed in a number of posts here over the last couple of months , the US is very likely to do precisely that.</p>
			<p id="p42">You should further note that there’s a G20 summit scheduled for London for April 2 and climate change is going to be high on the agenda. Also, according to the FT , the UNSG wants “… to convene a meeting of 30 to 40 heads of state in February or March to draw up a new framework for tackling the issue.” (Got all those acronyms? You can’t do IR without the acronyms.)</p>
			<p id="p43">Tuesday, January 27 8:34 am EST</p>
			<p id="p44">A truly thoughtful essay from Harry Eyres, Freedom and the price of oil , appeared in this past weekend’s “FT.” It’s a meditation, to a great extent, on the ecologist Ivan Illich . Eyres writes of Illich: “He had the barmy-seeming idea that we would do better - that is to say would lead more human, fairer and freer lives - if we consumed less energy. Far from freeing us up, the addiction to ever-greater quanta of energy enslaves our souls, making us passive consumers rather than active doers, and concentrates power in mega-institutions.”</p>
			<p id="p45">I wrote on a similar theme about a year ago: “Can we reduce our dangerous rates of consumption and maintain and improve our standards of living worldwide? You bet. Making Peace with the Planet will also make us happier. You can take that to the bank.” (See Galloping Consumption .)</p>
			<p id="p46">Or, as Bill McKibben wrote in a review of Tom Friedman’s Hot, Flat and Crowded, “Does it ever occur to him, in the grip of a fantasia like this, that if the sun is shining brightly, or the breeze is blowing steadily, you could dry your clothes on a $14 piece of rope strung off your back deck, or for that matter on a foldable rack in the apartment hallway? And that since most of the world already knows how to do it, we might be smarter moving in their direction instead of insisting that they buy into our entire high-technology suburban dream?” (See my review of McKibben’s review here .)</p>
			<p id="p47">Monday, January 26 12:39 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p48">Obama takes steps to reverse Bush climate policies is the headline from Reuters. For one thing, the new President has instructed the EPA to revisit California’s application to institute carbon dioxide limits on motor vehicles sold there. (See California Standards here .) See also this from the “Washington Post” today, including the video of Obama’s announcement in which he said, among other things, “The days of Washington dragging its heels are over.”</p>
			<p id="p49">He also ordered the Department of Transportation to accelerate the schedule for bringing new fuel-efficient cars into the market, as required by the federal energy bill from December 2007.</p>
			<p id="p50">The “WaPo” also reported that “Separately, the State Department is expected to name Todd Stern , formerly a senior official in the Clinton administration, as the new U.S. envoy on climate change. Here is the introduction by Sec. of State Hillary Rodham Clinton and remarks from Stern - text and video .</p>
			<p id="p51">Stern is a senior fellow at the Center for American Progress and, as such, has been instrumental in developing policy recommendations that the new administration has been embracing. At the core of this is the transformation to a low-carbon economy with all the potential for jobs and development that that can mean. See Capturing the Energy Opportunity: Creating a Low-Carbon Economy from the CAP.</p>
			<p id="p52">Opportunity continues to be one of my favorite words.</p>
			<p id="p53">Here’s CAP’s video on their plan.</p>
			<p id="p54">Friday, January 23 3:36 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p55">New International Agency - AFP (via Yahoo) had this to say the other day: Germany hails creation of global climate-change agency . More than 100 countries are to be represented in Bonn next week for the founding conference of the International Renewable Energy Agency (IRENA).</p>
			<p id="p56">Here’s how the new agency describes itself: “Mandated by governments worldwide, IRENA aims at becoming the main driving force in promoting a rapid transition towards the widespread and sustainable use of renewable energy on a global scale. Acting as the global voice for renewable energies, IRENA will provide practical advice and support for both industrialised and developing countries, help them improve their regulatory frameworks and build capacity.”</p>
			<p id="p57">For more on IRENA, read their comprehensive brochure , available in English, German, French, Arabic and Spanish. See also their presentation . The timing is excellent for the advent of this potentially critical international agency.</p>
			<p id="p58">Less is More - “GreenerBuildings” reports here on an Electric Power Research Institute study that “energy users in the U.S. could reduce the growth rate of consumption by 22 percent in the next 20 years — a reduction equivalent to 14 times the electricity used annually in New York City” Sweet! (I have looked at efficiency a good number of times here, including in More Groundbreaking Work on Efficiency and Good Grief, More Efficiency .)</p>
			<p id="p59">Special “FT” Report - In another sterling bit of journalism from the “FT,” see this look at Clean Energy from earlier this week. There are articles on the green economy, the smart grid, microgeneration, among other key topics, as well as videos and an excellent interactive graphic on green building. Don’t miss this fine report.</p>
			<p id="p60">Massachusetts and Wind - Following up on my note on offshore wind below (Jan. 19), the Governor of Massachusetts, Deval Patrick, is calling for 2GW of wind capacity by 2020. See this from RenewableEnergyWorld.com . “wind power is going to be a centerpiece of the clean energy economy we are creating for Massachusetts,” said Patrick. This can supply 10% of Massachusetts’s present electricity demand.</p>
			<p id="p61">I’m In With the In Crowd - An interesting story from “US News &amp; World Report” has this perspective: The New In-Crowd in Obama’s Washington: the Renewable Energy Folks . Where were the in-crowd members on Tuesday night? At the Green Ball , where else? ”Among the several hundred attendees were a large number of D.C. lobbyists, environmentalists, and trade association officials. They sat at small tables (with green tablecloths) or stood around in small groups, discussing topics like the nuances of carbon cap-and-trade legislation.” Well, as the late, great Ron McKernan , Pigpen to most , was wont to say: “That’s what I’m talking about!”</p>
			<p id="p62">Thursday, January 22 1:41 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p63">Remember Drill, Baby, Drill? Well, it’s going to be more about actual good public policy based on sound science in the brave new world of the Obama administration.</p>
			<p id="p64">From “The Economist” comes Blessed are the geeks, for they shall inherit the Earth . I’ve touched on some of these folks at Obama’s Team and Obama’s Team, Continued . In “The Economist,” we are told “These appointments, therefore, mark a shift in political attitudes towards scientific advice. When he announced his selections Mr. Obama said that promoting science is not just about providing resources (though he has promised to double the budget for basic science research over the next decade), but also about promoting free inquiry and listening to what scientists have to say, ‘especially when it is inconvenient.’” (Get the “inconvenient” allusion? If not, try this .)</p>
			<p id="p65">See also The Holdren Factor from “Seed” on John Holdren, the new President’s incoming chief science advisor.</p>
			<p id="p66">I mentioned the political interference with climate science here last year and toward the end of this post nearly two years ago. The venerable Union of Concerned Scientists have had quite a lot of important things to say over the years about Scientific Integrity as well.</p>
			<p id="p67">In any event, here is the new Energy Secretary, Nobel laureate Steven Chu, responding to questions posed during the transition from the public. He’s, as I noted in yesterday’s post, one of a group of focused, smart, committed, progressive folks that Obama is bringing to bear on the critical issues of energy, the environment and climate change.</p>
			<p id="p68">Wednesday, January 21 9:57 am EST</p>
			<p id="p69">The White House website already has a page on the “New Energy for America” plan. They’re on it!</p>
			<p id="p70">An article in this week’s edition of “EERE Network News” from DOE’s Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, talks about President Obama’s inaugural address and its reference to renewables: how the US will “harness the sun and the winds and the soil to fuel our cars and run our factories.” It also notes that the address confronted climate change by saying “with old friends and former foes, we will work tirelessly to … roll back the specter of a warming planet.”</p>
			<p id="p71">The new Secretary of the Interior, Ken Salazar, has said “I will be a strong and forceful advocate for the wise stewardship of our nation’s land and water resources, I will help us build a clean energy economy for the twenty-first century ” (See the release .)</p>
			<p id="p72">For more on the focused, smart, committed, progressive group that Obama has assembled on energy, the environment and climate change, see Obama’s Team and Obama’s Team, Continued .</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>