<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Forests | Climate Change - Health and Environmental Effects | U.S. EPA</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Forests | Climate Change - Health and Environmental Effects | U.S. EPA</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2009-10-15 23:37:13.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/effects/forests.html</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>Climate change</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>global warming</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>environmental effects</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>forests</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>climate factors</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>tree growth</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>fire risk</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>carbon dioxide fertilization</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>carbon sequestration</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/ENV_EN/13401.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change ( IPCC, 2007 ) concluded that there may be significant regional transitions associated with shifts in forest location and composition in the U.S. due to climate change. Climate change is likely to alter the geographic distribution of North American forests, including regionally important tree species, such as New England sugar maples and boreal forests in Alaska.</p>
			<p id="p2">The effects of climate change on forests in the U.S. and other parts of the world will depend not only on climatic factors but also on stresses from pollution (e.g., acid rain); future trends in forest management practices, including fire control and demand for timber; and land-use change. It is difficult to separate the influence of climate change from these other pressures.</p>
			<p id="p3">Climate change effects on forests are likely to include changes in forest health and productivity and changes in the geographic range of certain tree species. These effects can in turn alter timber production, outdoor recreational activities, water quality, wildlife and rates of carbon storage.</p>
			<p id="p4">Climate Factors</p>
			<p id="p5">In general, forests are sensitive to climatic variability and change. Climatic factors that influence forest health-temperature, rainfall, atmospheric levels of carbon dioxide (CO2) and other greenhouse gases and extreme weather and fire events—are changing and are expected to continue changing due to human activities.</p>
			<p id="p6">The following climate factors are likely to play an important role in determining future forest conditions:</p>
			<p id="p7">Air temperature</p>
			<p id="p8">Atmospheric CO2 concentrations</p>
			<p id="p9">Climatic variability and the frequency and severity of extreme events</p>
			<p id="p10">Indirect effects on pollution levels such as tropospheric ozone</p>
			<p id="p11">Temperature and Precipitation</p>
			<p id="p12">Changes in temperature and precipitation are expected to change forest location, composition, and productivity. Climate change is likely to drive the migration of tree species, resulting in changes in the geographic distribution of forest types and new combinations of species within forests. In North America, many tree species may shift northward or to higher elevations. ( IPCC, 2007 )</p>
			<p id="p13">Free-Air CO2 Enrichment ( FACE</p>
			<p id="p14">) experiments suggest that tree growth rates may increase with increasing levels of atmospheric CO2, but these effects are expected to saturate over time as tree communities adjust to increased CO2 levels.</p>
			<p id="p15">Climate change effects that influence tree growth will also alter rates of carbon storage (or sequestration) in trees and soils. Increased carbon sequestration would remove more CO2 from the atmosphere (a negative feedback that lessens climate change), whereas carbon losses through forest disturbances would result in more CO2 entering the atmosphere (a positive feedback that strengthens climate change). The IPCC ( 2007 ) concludes that “net carbon uptake by terrestrial ecosystems is likely to peak before mid-century and then weaken or even reverse, thus amplifying climate change.”</p>
			<p id="p16">Fire and Disease</p>
			<p id="p17">Changes in forest disturbance regimes, such as fire or disease, could also affect the future of U.S. forests and the market for forest products, such as timber. Increased temperatures could increase fire risk in areas that become drier due to climate change. These changes could compound existing fire risks ( IPCC, 2007 ). Climate change could also promote the rapid increase of diseases and pests that attack tree species. Such disturbances may be detrimental to forests themselves, but may have a lesser impact at the market level due to salvage operations that harvest timber from dying forests ( Shugart, et al., 2003 ).</p>
			<p id="p18">The IPCC concluded that, for North America as a whole ( IPCC, 2007 ):</p>
			<p id="p19">Climate change is expected to increase the growth of forests modestly (by 10-20 percent) over the next century. However, extreme and/or long-term climate change scenarios also create the potential for widespread forest decline.</p>
			<p id="p20">Disturbances such as wildfires and insect outbreaks are increasing and likely to intensify in a warmer climate with drier soils and longer growing seasons. The forest fire season is likely to lengthen, and the area subject to high fire danger is likely to increase significantly.</p>
			<p id="p21">The long-term effects of fire will depend heavily on changes in human fire management activities.</p>
			<p id="p22">Contribution of Working Group II to the Fourth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [Parry, Martin L., Canziani, Osvaldo F., Palutikof, Jean P., van der Linden, Paul J., and Hanson, Clair E. (eds.)]. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom, 1000 pp.</p>
			<p id="p23">. Contribution of Working Group II to the Third Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [McCarthy, James J., Canziani, Osvaldo F., Leary, Neil A., Dokken, David J., and White, Kasey S. (eds.)]. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA, 1032pp.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>