<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>
Climate Change Articles
</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>
Climate Change Articles
</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-07 11:33:13.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://climatechangearticles.blogspot.com/</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/ENV_EN/2190.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Climate change is man-made?</p>
			<p id="p2">Despite many promises and strong support from president Obama, US still failed to pass cap-and- trade legislation, as there is still not enough political will for such action, or as some others would say fossil fuels lobbies are still too powerful. The only somewhat good news came from climate negotiator Todd Stern who recently said that despite the failure of cap-and-trade legislation US won’t change its target for 2020 to reduce greenhouse-gas emissions by approximately 17 percent.</p>
			<p id="p3">If you follow what's happening with climate change legislation in United States then you already know that The House approved a bill last year to set limits on carbon emissions linked to climate change but this bill stalled in Senate. Though cap-and-trade legislation would be more than welcome passing this bill will take some time, and in the meantime Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) needs to step in, and use existing laws to at least regulate some sources of carbon pollution.</p>
			<p id="p4">By the current looks of it, EPA will not be afraid to use these laws, and the EPA regulation planned for next year will set the U.S.’s first nationwide limits on greenhouse-gas pollution in the effort to curb global warming. This is a clear sign that EPA will continue pushing forward towards the adequate climate change legislation.</p>
			<p id="p5">Many political analysts believe that the adequate domestic climate change legislation is the key to success to the international climate deal. Copenhagen was yet another big failure on international stage, mainly because US failed to give positive examples to other countries. Hopefully, this situation will soon improve.</p>
			<p id="p6">The majority of scientists believes that climate change is not only the real thing but that we are also yet to see the worst the climate change has to offer. Climate change is already there and we need to adapt to it as quickly as possible. This lead us to a question can today's science also predict what will our future climate look like?</p>
			<p id="p7">My answer is no, there are too much factors that affect our climate so scientists despite all their efforts are still far away from being able to predict future climate change. Scientists have already discovered bunch of different factors that have serious impact on climate change, and there are probably many factors that are yet to be discovered, not to mention finding interlinking between these factors. In other words, climate change phenomenon is still too complex for today's science.</p>
			<p id="p8">Yes, ice is melting, and yes, temperatures are rising on global level but how much will temperature rise in years to come is impossible to tell. Increase in global temperature isn't only connected with the amount of carbon emissions but with many other factors, and only by incorporating all these factors we could be able to give some decent prediction. The problem? We still don't know half of these factors so we can't really set the equation.</p>
			<p id="p9">Climate change science is still pretty much tapping in the dark hoping that somewhere there's the right switch to turn the lights on. What this basically means is that we are still swimming in theory waters, meaning that there are many possible scenarios for future climate change. The only bad thing is that most of these scenarios were made for the disaster movies.</p>
			<p id="p10">According to the latest scientific reports Earth is warming up rapidly, and this should in short-term increase the global amount of rainfall. The scientists have even calculated that the rainfall will increase globally by 2-3 per cent for every degree Celsius that the Earth's surface heats up, so by the current looks of it we are in for a heavy rainfall in years to come.</p>
			<p id="p11">There are some scientists who do not totally agree with this theory claiming that this calculation won't work if the balance of factors causing global warming changes significantly. There are several different factors that will have significant effect on the amount of rainfall in years to come such as the level of solar radiation, the amount of greenhouse gases, etc.</p>
			<p id="p12">One of the less known but still very important factors are dark aerosols that have the ability to absorb enough sunlight in the atmosphere to suppress the expected rainfall response to increased temperatures, and the immediate result of this could be less rainfall.</p>
			<p id="p13">When discussing this rather interesting topic Dr Timothy Andrews, scientist at the University of Leeds, said that two effects should be counted together because they go in tandem: "a fast atmospheric response that is closely linked with the type of climate change mechanism, and a slower response to surface temperature change that happens regardless of the climate change mechanism."</p>
			<p id="p14">According to him these slow effects do produce the predicted 2-3 per cent increase in rainfall but fast atmospheric response might change all of this, depending on factors involved (such as dark aerosols).</p>
			<p id="p15">There will be more rainfall if the current balance of factors remains pretty much the same in years the come. If by any chance this balance changes due to increased significance of certain factor we can even expect less rainfall in years to come.</p>
			<p id="p16">Climate change protests are becoming more frequent in Australia and many hope that this will create enough political pressure to urge the major political parties to take action on climate change.</p>
			<p id="p17">Tens of thousands of climate change protesters in Adelaide, Brisbane, Canberra, Darwin, Hobart, Melbourne, Sydney and Perth have protested against current climate change policy.</p>
			<p id="p18">The politicians still fail to adequately punish big polluters, and many people believe that the time has come for politicians to step up and take responsibility because climate change needs quick action.</p>
			<p id="p19">The public is very disappointed with false promises, constant delays, and wants to see real action in form of strict laws that would curb carbon pollution in Australia.</p>
			<p id="p20">There were also dozens of climate change skeptics who tried to disrupt rally in some cities but they failed to do so. The only thing they managed to do was to create minor incidents which police had to break up.</p>
			<p id="p21">These events could be very helpful because many politicians will be forced to listen what their voters want from them, and perhaps politics will become more ignorant to powerful fossil fuel lobbies that delay major political decisions connected with climate change.</p>
			<p id="p22">If you ask climate change scientists about the connection between climate change and ocean circulation many of them will tell you that there is a very strong connection between these two. A team of scientists from the University of Cardiff has managed to find the evidence which connects fluctuations in ocean circulation to the climate change and temperature.</p>
			<p id="p23">The primary focus of their study was Atlantic meridional overturning circulation that carries tropical surface waters northwards, and cold deep water from the North Atlantic southwards to fill the Atlantic basin. In Atlantic basin this water gets mixed with deep waters that originate in the Antarctic region.</p>
			<p id="p24">Ocean circulation.</p>
			<p id="p25">Climate change scientists already know that in times when ocean circulation is strong, heat is moved efficiently from the tropics to the poles, and when the circulation is weak the poles become colder.</p>
			<p id="p26">Scientists believe that that during particularly cold periods in the last ice age Atlantic meridional overturning circulation was very weakened, and when this circulation strengthens after a period of weak circulation, it doesn't just return to its "normal" extent but it gets stronger than before.</p>
			<p id="p27">The lead author of this study, Dr Stephen Barker from Cardiff University, explained this very vividly by saying "when the circulation kicks back in, it comes back with a vengeance".</p>
			<p id="p28">These changes in ocean circulation are extremely important, and according to a scientific analysis they were responsible for the increase of 9 degrees Celsius over the course of just a few decades, 14,600 years ago.</p>
			<p id="p29">So many factors influence climate change, and ocean circulation looks to be among the most important ones.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>