<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Climate Change - Part 6</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Climate Change - Part 6</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-07 18:12:17.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://climatechange.foreignpolicyblogs.com/page/6/</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/ENV_EN/7560.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Wednesday, May 19 9:24 am EST</p>
			<p id="p2">Monday, May 17 3:58 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p3">So at this point I have the score, in a sane world, about ten to nothing against nuclear power. (See previous two posts below.) Here are a few more points against:</p>
			<p id="p4">Perhaps the most telling argument against nuclear power, in market economies anyway, is the failure of nuclear power to compete. Amory Lovins, in his magisterial “ Four Nuclear Myths ,” notes: “To be sure, some centrally planned power systems do continue to order and build nuclear plants regardless, almost always drawing directly or indirectly on the public purse.” (That’s the secret of France’s “success,” by the way.)</p>
			<p id="p5">But what about nuclear when capital from investors is at stake? “Nuclear power is continuing its decades-long collapse in the global marketplace because it’s grossly uncompetitive, unneeded, and obsolete.” (See more at Rocky Mountain Institute’s “ Nuclear Power: Climate Fix or Folly? “)</p>
			<p id="p6">Al Gore says it this way in Our Choice : “…the driving force that has converted once vibrant nuclear dreams into debilitating nightmares for electric utilities has been the grossly unacceptable economics of the present generation of reactors.”</p>
			<p id="p7">What to do? Massive public subsidy of nuclear power would be one approach. But, as Gore notes, “Even massive government subsidies and guarantees have failed to attract much private investment back …” Hundreds of billions of dollars can’t buy you new nuclear power, at least not yet. Oh, by the way, the risk of default on loan guarantees is above 50 percent. The Senate, via the American Power Act , and the Obama Administration want to give away nuclear power, but there still don’t seem to be many takers.</p>
			<p id="p8">Meanwhile, across the pond, the new British coalition government , may have, by its appointment of Liberal Democrat Chris Huhne as minister for Energy and Climate Change, sounded the death knell for new nuclear power. Nuclear will not get atom of help from this Government reads the headline from “The Times.” Citigroup reported last November, for Britain, The Economics Say No - without massive amounts of public money. With as Homeric a public debt as Greece, the UK is not about to sink billions of pounds into the black hole of new nuclear.</p>
			<p id="p9">Here are a few more nails for the coffin. Environmental impact : Indian Point, on the Hudson River, accounts for the deaths of about a billion fish a year. Inadequacy of water supply : During the devastating European heat wave in the summer of 2003, France, Spain and Germany were forced to shut down numerous nuclear plants and reduce the power output of others because of low water supplies. Reliability: Nuclear power’s much-vaunted reliability comes up against some stark numbers. Lovins - perhaps not surprisingly - again: “A broader assessment of reliability tends not to favor nuclear power. Of all 132 U.S. nuclear plants built-just over half of the 253 originally ordered-21% were permanently and prematurely closed due to reliability or cost problems. Another 27% have completely failed for a year or more at least once.”</p>
			<p id="p10">I’ve found nuclear power wanting for nearly 40 years. I read John Gofman and Arthur Tamplin’s superb Poisoned Power when it first came out. If there has been any argument that might mitigate the manifest evils of nuclear power in all these decades it is that the climate crisis requires us to produce low-carbon energy. But, as we’ve seen, that is a Big Lie. It is very clear indeed that further pursuit of the “nuclear option” will in fact take us closer, and more quickly, to climate catastrophe.</p>
			<p id="p11">It’s time to pull the plug on nukes. Wake up and smell the clean tech .</p>
			<p id="p12">Saturday, May 15 10:27 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p13">Yesterday I mentioned a number of big-ticket reasons to think that nuclear power is a very bad bet indeed: It bleeds money from smarter, cheaper and much more climate-friendly options; it’s dangerous; it’s radically inefficient; it’s not, at the end of the day - that is to say, through the whole life cycle - a particularly low-carbon approach, certainly relative to wind and solar; and we don’t have an inexhaustible supply of fissionable material.</p>
			<p id="p14">There are many more reasons why nukes are the wrong path: waste for instance. Here is an FT article that talks about some of the problems in the US. After spending nearly $9 billion on Yucca Mountain , the proposed long-term high-level disposal facility, President Obama pulled the plug last year. (Politics? Don’t ask.) Meanwhile, there are tens of thousands of tons of radioactive waste languishing at civilian nuclear reactor sites in the US alone, not to mention “22,000 canisters of solid defense-related radioactive waste for future disposal in a repository,” according to the DOE.</p>
			<p id="p15">And, according to UNEP here : “Since the 1960s, more than 200,000 tons of spent fuel have been produced by 400 reactors in 30 countries, and every year 10,000 tons are added.” UNEP also estimates the global waste plutonium burden from nuclear weaponry in excess of a thousand tons.</p>
			<p id="p16">Is there a safe, environmentally acceptable way to dispose of nuclear waste ? Not yet, according to Greenpeace here . What about reprocessing the waste into fuel? “Reprocessing of spent nuclear fuel would increase, not decrease, the total volume of nuclear waste.” That’s what the Union of Concerned Scientists says here . Oh, by the way, any idea how long you need to keep the high-level waste fully isolated in order to protect public health? Well, just one constituent of this waste among many, Plutonium-239, has a half-life of 24,000 years. That means that you have to think in terms of segregating it safely for hundreds of thousands of years.</p>
			<p id="p17">Can you watch over and protect this waste for all this time? See this new movie, Into Eternity , about long-term radioactive waste storage. The director was interviewed recently on NPR . From the interview: “But in 1995, the Academy of Science was asked whether it is possible to, on a scientific ground, to say that it is possible to communicate to the future and it is possible to deter inadvertent human intrusion. And the question - the answer on that was, in both cases, no. It’s not possible to, on a scientific ground, to guarantee this.”</p>
			<p id="p18">So, even John Rowe, the CEO of Exelon, the utility with the largest nuclear fleet in the US, said “Until we have a plan in place to store waste in the long term, then we ought ‘to go slow’ on expanding nuclear power.” This from someone who has a rather large and serious vested interest in nukes!</p>
			<p id="p19">Logically, to what might you think all that highly radioactive material in all those places all over the world would lend itself? The threat of nuclear weapon proliferation and terrorism , perhaps? Others would agree. Among these are the very good people at the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists. The group was founded “…in 1945 by scientists, engineers, and other experts who had created the atomic bomb as part of the Manhattan Project. They knew about the horrible effects of these new weapons and devoted themselves to warning the public about the consequences of using them.” Since then, their sense of responsibility has expanded to nuclear energy, biosecurity and, perhaps not surprisingly, climate change.</p>
			<p id="p20">Current efforts to encourage the global spread of nuclear energy are dangerously shortsighted and will result in weapons proliferation.</p>
			<p id="p21">International security must be the top priority in global nuclear energy policy, meaning the unbridled promotion of nuclear energy must stop.</p>
			<p id="p22">Oh, and by the way, the threat of terrorism does not come only from the theft of weapons-grade materials. It comes from the specter of sabotage at nuclear power facilities . That’s a happy prospect considering how close to major population centers many power plants are.</p>
			<p id="p23">Friday, May 14 2:09 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p24">I am, of course, borrowing from George H.W. Bush’s timeless declaration . But what’s really at issue here? There is no sense at all in building new nuclear capability in this country or, for that matter, any other.</p>
			<p id="p25">In my classes on climate change and on clean tech, I identify nuclear power, along with carbon capture and storage (CCS) and geoengineering, as red herrings. By this I mean that these are wasteful technologies that only distract us from the urgent task of restructuring our consumption and production patterns to allow the planet to cool down. This definition , from a treatise on logic and debate, says “The term red herring is sometimes used loosely to refer to any kind of diversionary tactic, such as presenting relatively unimportant arguments that will use up the other debaters’ speaking time and distract them from more important issues.” That’s precisely what the debate on nuclear power does: uses up our time, not to mention our money and energy, and distracts us from infinitely more fruitful pursuits.</p>
			<p id="p26">Here is a raft of reasons why we can’t afford new nukes and, in fact, nuclear power needs to be phased out:</p>
			<p id="p27">First and foremost, it siphons money from our efforts on real clean tech: energy efficiency, renewables, green building, etc. Amory Lovins, in his paper “ Four Nuclear Myths ” says it succinctly and eloquently: “…expanding nuclear power…will reduce and retard climate protection. That’s because…new nuclear power is so costly and slow that …it will save about 2-20 times less carbon per dollar, and about 20-40 times less carbon per year, than investing instead in the market winners-efficient use of electricity and…’micropower,’ comprising distributed renewables…and cogenerating electricity together with useful heat in factories and buildings.” (I made the same argument to the Chairman of the United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority a couple of years ago.)</p>
			<p id="p28">Danger: You might remember Three Mile Island and Chernobyl . You probably haven’t heard about the near-catastrophe at Davis-Besse in Ohio in early 2002. “Only a thin stainless steel veneer-less than one quarter-inch thick-had prevented a loss-of-coolant accident more serious than that at Three Mile Island in 1979. Had the corroded reactor vessel head ruptured, the loss of cooling water would likely have led to both a reactor meltdown and a containment failure.” (See p. 17 of this report from the Union of Concerned Scientists.) The longer the world’s 436 active nuclear power plants operate, the greater the chances of another Chernobyl happening. More reactors only up the danger.</p>
			<p id="p29">Waste Heat: Nuclear power only exists for central generating facilities powered by heat. Just as with coal or gas, nuclear fission heats water to produce steam which turns a turbine which turns a generator which produces electricity. Just about two-thirds of the energy that goes into producing the steam is lost as heat in these plants. Two-thirds ! So nuclear power is incredibly inefficient.</p>
			<p id="p30">Low Carbon? Not Really: One analyst, writing in Energy Policy recently, notes “…that nuclear power is not directly emitting greenhouse gas emissions, but rather that lifecycle emissions occur through plant construction, operation, uranium mining and milling, and plant decommissioning.” An article from Nature Reports Climate Change summarizes the findings thus: nuclear power is much less GHG-intensive than coal or gas, but much more than solar or wind - “…nuclear emits twice as much carbon as solar photovoltaic, at 32 gCO</p>
			<p id="p31">2</p>
			<p id="p32">2</p>
			<p id="p33">e/kWh.”</p>
			<p id="p34">Limitless Supplies of Fissionable Material? Not really: The Lean Guide to Nuclear Energy says “Shortages of uranium - and the lack of realistic alternatives - leading to interruptions in supply, can be expected to start in the middle years of the decade 2010-2019, and to deepen thereafter.”</p>
			<p id="p35">(There’s much more to say, but I’m going to leave this for the moment and continue it over the course of the next several days. To tell you the truth, it’s gorgeous Spring weather outside and I need to get out there.)</p>
			<p id="p36">Wednesday, May 12 1:57 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p37">To tell you that I haven’t been skeptical about the value of a weak Senate climate and energy bill would be lying to you. For one thing, I’m pretty happy with how the EPA has been approaching the regulation of greenhouse gases . I’d hate to see strong programs like this and the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative (RGGI) and Western Climate Initiative (WCI) get swept aside by something less effective. The House vehicle, the American Clean Energy and Security Act - aka Waxman-Markey, is a strong piece of legislation, covering all the bases. I’d also hate to see a nuclear power revival in this country, or even just more billions upon billions go down the toilet while we are in easy reach of a 100% renewable energy economy.</p>
			<p id="p38">In any event, the Senate, after months of negotiation with the White House, internally among Senators, with the House leadership, and certainly with industry and environmentalists, has rolled out its package . John Kerry has been spearheading the bill and had this to say today: “We have a never-before-seen coalition from across America, including key stakeholders embracing energy and climate legislation for the first time ever.” Some key players from core constituencies had comment . Frances Beinecke, President, Natural Resources Defense Council : “The core carbon pollution limits in the bill, covering all major pollution sources, are a solid foundation for Senate legislation.” Jim Rogers, CEO, Duke Energy : “The legislation can help the U.S. get its economic ‘mojo’ back. Operation Free : “America’s military leadership … have all identified climate change and oil dependence as security threats.” Roger Johnson, President, National Farmers Union : “We strongly support economic incentives from the climate change bill to enable agriculture to play a positive role.”</p>
			<p id="p39">A short summary of the bill reveals that there are “…separate, targeted mechanisms for the three major emitting sectors: power plants, heavy industry and transportation.” I will leave deeper analysis off for the time being and defer to keen minds like Joe Romm at Climate Progress who asks here if the bill meets critically important criteria , like dropping the US substantially below its business-as-usual path on greenhouse gases. He says yes.</p>
			<p id="p40">On eventual passage of this legislation, David Roberts at Grist , says “Chances for passage are quite slim, but not as slim as generally perceived, and ironically, the path to passage now involves the bill getting stronger, not weaker.”</p>
			<p id="p41">Remember too, that the rest of the world is looking to the US to come back to the table with strong further proposals for an international regime. Lest we forget, the European Union’s climate chief, Connie Hedegaard, had a lot to say on this recently.</p>
			<p id="p42">I keep trying to have an open mind. Maybe a strong bill, not unlike Waxman-Markey, can come out of all this and become law. We’ll just have to see.</p>
			<p id="p43">In the meantime, you can watch John Kerry on the bill. Even better, though, you can read his eminently convincing post at Grist.</p>
			<p id="p44">Tuesday, May 11 2:39 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p45">I was a fan of Gordon Brown on climate change. Among other virtues, he was outspoken about the Denialists and he picked up the ball on climate finance and ran with it after Copenhagen. He is leaving No. 10 today and David Cameron will soon be the new Prime Minister. See this from the AP.</p>
			<p id="p46">So what’s that mean for climate change and energy policy in the UK? Thankfully, the British Conservative Party is a lot less conservative on these issues than other conservative parties in other countries, some of which I won’t name - like the Republican Party in the US. (Oops, I did. Sorry.)</p>
			<p id="p47">Here is the Conservative webpage for these issues. They seem committed to offshore power and to distributed generation. Like Labor, though, they are also committed to time and money-wasting boondoggles like CCS and nuclear power . The funny thing is on nuclear power, though, that they are for “Clearing the way for new nuclear power stations - provided they receive no public subsidy.” That’s fine with me, because as Citigroup reported last November, in Britain The Economics Say No - without massive amounts of public money. With as Homeric a public debt as Greece, the UK is not about to sink billions of pounds into the black hole of new nuclear.</p>
			<p id="p48">Meanwhile, the Tories’ junior partner in government, the Liberal Democrats, are fully committed to a “smart decentralised grid” in a “zero-carbon Britain.” Their webpage on Energy and Climate Change is also unequivocal about nukes: “More nuclear power will soak up subsidy, centralise energy production and hinder development of Britain’s vast renewable resources. Nuclear has a dirty legacy and increases global security risks. We oppose construction of further nuclear power stations.” Hear, hear.</p>
			<p id="p49">Let’s hope the new government steers a steady course toward renewables, energy efficiency, and a “zero-carbon Britain.”</p>
			<p id="p50">Monday, May 10 12:18 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p51">I wrote about The Melting Himalayas over a year ago. Notwithstanding the relatively absurd brouhaha in January caused by the discovery of a one-paragraph error in the 4th Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, research on glacier loss in the Himalayas has been continuing apace. The minor peccadillo in the report was trumpeted, far and wide, by climate change Denialists, and vastly inflated by the media - as they will do.</p>
			<p id="p52">Orville Schell, Editor-in-Chief of “ China Green ,” a multimedia enterprise of the Asia Society, has an informative piece on the glaciers in the latest “NY Review of Books.” Schell surveys some key issues, like the impact of warming and black carbon on the glaciers. He quotes Jim Hansen to the effect that “continued ‘business-as-usual’ emission of greenhouse gases and black soot will result in the loss of most Himalayan glaciers this century, with devastating effects on fresh water supplies.” That’s water that serves a billion people in East, Southeast, and South Asia, give or take a few million - and depending on how far into the future we’re looking at and the populations then.</p>
			<p id="p53">(CSM)</p>
			<p id="p54">For more on the Himalayas, see On Thinner Ice , also from the Asia Society, and The Third Pole , from ChinaDialogue.</p>
			<p id="p55">Meanwhile, the countries whose people have the most to lose by the continuing melting of the Third Pole that supplies so much of their water, India and China, are continuing to rely on coal, the greatest single contributor to the greenhouse gas superheating the climate system. Here’s an item from the FT that indicates that India is at least looking at the environmental impacts of coal extraction on its forests. Over in China, the coal train keep coming. In fact, it’s a runaway train. According to this from the Post Carbon Institute, “China’s coal output grew an astonishing 28.1 percent from first quarter 2009 to first quarter 2010, to over 750 million metric tons consumed in just the past three months.” The article, though, reports that China is running out of coal and surveys some of its options, including renewables and nuclear power. See also this characteristically informative article from Keith Bradsher at the “NYT.” He writes: “The increase in oil and coal-fired electricity consumption in the first quarter was twice as fast as economic growth of about 12 percent for that period, a sign that rising energy consumption is not just the result of a rebounding economy but also of changes in the mix of industrial activity. The shift in activity is partly because of China’s economic stimulus program, which has resulted in a surge in public works construction that requires a lot of steel and cement.”</p>
			<p id="p56">The question for the health of poor Planet Earth - including the 6,820,104,232 people as of today - is whether or not the Indians and the Chinese are going to get out of the coal business in time.</p>
			<p id="p57">The FT covered their climate change meeting in Beijing this past weekend and reported here that the two Asian superpowers “…said it would be very difficult to achieve a strong international agreement on climate change at the summit in Mexico later this year…” My question is, given past performance , how hard will they try?</p>
			<p id="p58">Saturday, May 8 10:36 am EST</p>
			<p id="p59">I told one of my classes last week, after the Gulf of Mexico disaster , that the next time I heard someone talk about the romance of the internal combustion engine, I was going to deck them.</p>
			<p id="p60">As with coal, so with oil. (See last post below.) We don’t need it, and the sooner we transition to the technology-driven economy , the easier we are all going to be able to breathe - literally and figuratively. I quoted a “NYT” story here to the effect that, at a recent international auto show, “…the internal-combustion engine seemed almost passé.”</p>
			<p id="p61">Well, aside from hybrids and EVs, there’s the fuel cell car. It’s about time, it seems to me. Honda is coming out with the FCX Clarity . Seems like a blockbuster to me. Emissions? No carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide, hydrocarbons, oxides of nitrogen, or particulates. Only water vapor. ZEV works for me. You?</p>
			<p id="p62">For an entertaining look at hydrogen fuel cell vehicles, see Click and Clack on Nova here . In Iceland, not incidentally, they’re going to make their hydrogen with 100% renewable energy, hydro or geothermal.</p>
			<p id="p63">And take a closer look here at how the Clarity works.</p>
			<p id="p64">Friday, May 7 5:22 pm EST</p>
			<p id="p65">I wrote a couple of weeks ago that we most certainly can eliminate coal-fired power plants . Well, according to the US Energy Information Administration (EIA), we not only can, we’re on that track now. How? The answer lies partly in the switch to natural gas.</p>
			<p id="p66">The FT quotes the EIA here : “… in 2009, the carbon intensity of the electric power sector decreased by nearly 4.3 percent, primarily due to fuel switching as the price of coal rose 6.8 percent from 2008 to 2009 while the comparable price of natural gas fell 48 percent on a per Btu basis.” And gas is not only cheaper, it’s, as we know, much cleaner than coal. Here’s a chart from the folks at America’s Natural Gas Alliance (ANGA) that illustrates to what extent.</p>
			<p id="p67">These are convincing numbers.</p>
			<p id="p68">The FT story is in the context of the fact that in the US “…carbon emissions fell 7 per cent in 2009 - the biggest fall since the records begin in 1949, according to the EIA.”</p>
			<p id="p69">This chart from the EIA tells the story of the ongoing power industry fuel-switching from coal to oil.</p>
			<p id="p70">The FT says “The death of US coal, it seems, is marching on.” Dead man walking, in my view.</p>
			<p id="p71">(AFP)</p>
			<p id="p72">The Petersberg Climate Dialogue took place near Bonn this week. German Chancellor Angela Merkel and Mexican President Felipe Calderón brought together environment and climate ministers from 45 countries to “discuss what concrete steps should be taken” prior to the next UNFCCC “Conference of the Parties” (COP) in Cancún in December.</p>
			<p id="p73">Merkel said prior to these talks that it was necessary to “to find a basis of trust.” This AFP story quotes her further: “One thing that did not work well in Copenhagen is that a small circle met and the regional groups felt left out of the debate.” ( I’m not sure that I agree with her , but it’s entirely possible she’s stroking. Very good politician, Merkel.) The story also notes that Germany and Switzerland are calling now for raising the target for Europe to reduce its greenhouse gas emissions from 20 to 30 percent from 1990 levels by 2020. This will significantly up the ante for other countries and set an excellent example.</p>
			<p id="p74">Outgoing UNFCCC Executive Secretary Yvo de Boer spoke at the conference. His speech outlined where he thinks the process of international climate negotiations is now. “Trust” was his theme as well. “Trust in the process needs to be rebuilt as a matter of urgency,” said de Boer. He identified several key policy issues for resolution:</p>
			<p id="p75">clarity on the long-term finance beyond 2012, and the financial architecture to manage the finances</p>
			<p id="p76">clarity on how to keep the average global temperature increase stays below 2° C</p>
			<p id="p77">a proper attention to the necessity of internationally funded action being measured, reported and verified thoroughly and well</p>
			<p id="p78">the future of the Kyoto Protocol</p>
			<p id="p79">As reported here by Bloomberg, the conference was thought to have brought “movement to the climate talks.” Mexico, the host for the COP this year, is taking it all very, very seriously. Their officials intend to do a lot of traveling this year “… to pave the way for specific agreements on adaptation, funding and technology…”</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>