<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Environmental Economics: Climate Change</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Environmental Economics: Climate Change</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-08 11:13:30.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://www.env-econ.net/climate_change/page/19/</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>environment</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>natural resources</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>economics</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/ENV_EN/9190.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">News, Opinion, Analysis</p>
			<p id="p2">Recent Comments</p>
			<p id="p3">June 18, 2009</p>
			<p id="p4">Duke Energy CEO Jim Rogers appeared to enjoy his Tuesday night turn on Comedy Central's “Colbert Report,” plugging Duke's commitment to corral greenhouse gases even as it builds two new coal-fired power plants.</p>
			<p id="p5">“I never turn the lights out, because that's when the ghosts come out,” host Stephen Colbert deadpanned.</p>
			<p id="p6">“You know, we love people like you!” Rogers laughed.</p>
			<p id="p7">“You can see my house from space,” Colbert added.</p>
			<p id="p8">Colbert's conservative stage persona claimed confusion over the “clean coal” that Duke and other utilities promise. “Same deal as calling myself a vegetarian because I like broccoli with my veal?”</p>
			<p id="p9">Rogers took the silliness in good humor, 'fessing that coal generates 70 percent of Duke's energy and his belief in global warming. He said Duke has to keep customers' lights on while figuring out how to capture the carbon dioxide that coal plants belch and store it underground.</p>
			<p id="p10">“Under the earth?” Colbert responded. “Well, then it's the mole people's problem.”</p>
			<p id="p11">Here is the link to the episode: </p>
			<p id="p12">This paper examines these broader economic considerations—jobs, incomes, and economic growth—through the lens of two government initiatives this year by the Obama administration and Congress. The first is the set of clean-energy provisions incorporated within the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act .... The second is the proposed American Clean Energy and Security Act ...</p>
			<p id="p13">Our analysis in this paper shows that these two measures operating together can generate roughly $150 billion per year in new clean-energy investments in the United States over the next decade. This estimated $150 billion in new spending annually includes government funding but is notably dominated by private-sector investments. We estimate this sustained expansion in clean-energy investments triggered by the economic stimulus program and the forthcoming American Clean Energy and Security Act can generate a net increase of about 1.7 million jobs. This expansion in job opportunities can continue as long as the economy maintains a commitment to clean-energy investments in the $150 billion per year range.</p>
			<p id="p14">Dividing $150 billion by 1.7 million gives a green jobs cost estimate of $88,235 per job. Frankly, I'd rather see the benefits of $150 billion in clean energy measured as the value of environmental improvement. If we focus on the macroeconomic effects of government subsidized and mandated clean energy then green jobs are costs to society, not benefits, as they represent a more expensive way of producing goods and services. The benefits of subsidies and mandates should be measured as the value of the (1) improved health, recreation and ecological benefits and (2) climate change mitigation benefits of clean energy.</p>
			<p id="p15">Check out the new U.S. climate change report:</p>
			<p id="p16">On June 16, the U.S. Global Change Research Program released the NOAA-led study, " Global Climate Change Impacts in the United States " - a state of knowledge report about the observed and projected consequences of climate change for our nation and people. The document is an authoritative scientific report written in plain language, with the goal of better informing public and private decision making at all levels.</p>
			<p id="p17">From the inbox ("I've been reading your blog almost daily ... I've learned a lot there ... Would you please consider posting the following?"):</p>
			<p id="p18">The Union of Concerned Scientists is engaging Pennsylvania scientists and economists to emphasize the importance of taking action to mitigate the worst effects of climate change in the Commonwealth, and to point up the opportunities it offers for the Commonwealth to become a leader in renewable energy technology. Members of the Pennsylvania delegation represent key votes in the climate debate.</p>
			<p id="p19">The Pennsylvania Cover Letter to the Scientists and Economists' Call for Swift and Deep Cuts in Greenhouse Gas Emissions will be delivered to Pennsylvania representatives during the week of June 22nd and to senators later this summer or fall. The cover letter and underlying statement are open to Pennsylvania Ph.D. or doctoral candidate professionals with expertise relevant to our understanding of the scientific and economic dimensions of climate change, its impacts, and solutions. </p>
			<p id="p20">If you meet these criteria, we ask that you become a supporter. To read and sign the letter, visit http://www.ucsusa.org/global_</p>
			<p id="p21">Posted by John Whitehead on June 17, 2009 at 12:09 PM in Climate Change | Permalink | Comments (0)</p>
			<p id="p22">From the inbox:</p>
			<p id="p23">Breakthrough Institute is a small think tank in Oakland that has done some of the most rigorous analyses of the Waxman-Markey climate legislation to date. Our analysis of the bill demonstrates that the “cap” does not require any emissions reductions below business-as-usual estimates. In other words, it’s a cap in name only. The bill also includes a "renewable energy standard" that does not actually require any renewables to be deployed beyond what would be done without the bill.</p>
			<p id="p24">Here is a link to the PDF of the presentation: http://...BTI_ACES_Analysis_Briefing_June_17_09.pdf [17 mb].</p>
			<p id="p25">Here is a comment I left at the Energy Collective on a great post from Marc Gunther ( Kites, Coal and Waxman-Markey ):</p>
			<p id="p26">Mark, great post. One thing that tells me that W-M is about right, in terms of the economics of cap-and-trade, is the opposing forces on the extreme right and left. Economics tends to play down the middle and if the usual suspects on either side are opposed, then it is likely a good thing. Isn't that a weird rule-of-thumb? The problem with W-M is the 900+ pages. You don't need to read it or even skim it to know that it is full of government chosen winners and losers. As you well say, no one in the Obama administration or Congress knows how solutions are going to play out. Cranking up the economic incentives by reigning in the number of CO2 permits more quickly would get the markets to find a more efficient solution (i.e., consumers and business firms making choices that lead to new technology).</p>
			<p id="p27">Above I abbreviate Waxman-Markey with W-M but I wonder if this is descriptive enough. It could also stand in for Walmart or Wee man. Instead, how about Wax-Mark or Wax-ey or Wa-key (pronounced wackey).</p>
			<p id="p28">Here are a couple of emailed comments on my survey (I’ve gotten 286 so far!):</p>
			<p id="p29">A key factor in answering this question should be not only the broad instrument (tax vs cat), but also the level of stringency. There are also the other multiple design elements of each policy instrument (banking, borrowing, coverage, revenue raising and use, etc). I think the question of tax vs cat is overly simplistic and masks the many additional elements of policy design that survey takers have in the back of their minds as they answer the question.</p>
			<p id="p30">I thought about that but knew that if I tried to cover all the bases I’d spend too much time on the survey and I’d be less likely to get plenty of responses. The big thing that I am interested in is the perception that all economists strongly favor a carbon tax. It looks like that is not the case. However:</p>
			<p id="p31">Your lead in sentence (During the past year I've been asked several times whether all environmental economists prefer a carbon tax over cap-and-trade. I don't know the answer but I'd sure like to find out) is likely to influence your results.</p>
			<p id="p32">Hopefully, not too much.</p>
			<p id="p33">Oooops. I must be a libertarian.</p>
			<p id="p34">Posted by John Whitehead on June 03, 2009 at 09:00 AM in Climate Change | Permalink | Comments (3)</p>
			<p id="p35">I’m interested in your answers even if you don’t consider yourself an environmental economist.</p>
			<p id="p36">I'll be sure to post the results.</p>
			<p id="p37">The Obama administration and congressional Democrats have proposed a major cap-and-trade system aimed at reducing carbon dioxide emissions. Scientists agree that CO2 emissions around the world could lead to rising temperatures with serious long-term environmental consequences. But that is not a reason to enact a U.S. cap-and-trade system until there is a global agreement on CO2 reduction. The proposed legislation would have a trivially small effect on global warming while imposing substantial costs on all American households. And to get political support in key states, the legislation would abandon the auctioning of permits in favor of giving permits to selected corporations. ...</p>
			<p id="p38">The U.S. should wait until there is a global agreement on CO2 that includes China and India before committing to costly reductions in the United States. ...</p>
			<p id="p39">In my judgment, the proposed cap-and-trade system would be a costly policy that would penalize Americans with little effect on global warming. The proposal to give away most of the permits only makes a bad idea worse. Taxpayers and legislators should keep these things in mind before enacting any cap-and-trade system.</p>
			<p id="p40">My feeling is that there is little to no chance of global agreement until the U.S. shows that it is unilaterally committed to a climate change policy. Plus, there are significant co-benefits of reductions in energy use in the U.S. so the "no benefit" headline is a serious misrepresentation of the policy.</p>
			<p id="p41">As I drove to work this morning in my car of unknown ownership , I wondered what effect this would have on gas prices over the next couple of weeks ( from CNN.com ):</p>
			<p id="p42">Continental shelves beneath the retreating polar ice caps of the Arctic may hold almost double the amount of oil previously found in the region, scientists say.</p>
			<p id="p43">In new findings, the U.S. Geological Survey estimates the Arctic may be home to 30 percent of the planet's undiscovered natural gas reserves and 13 percent of its undiscovered oil.</p>
			<p id="p44">A team of scientists at the USGS collaborated with international researchers to conduct the first-ever comprehensive assessment of undiscovered oil and gas reserves within the Arctic Circle.</p>
			<p id="p45">Unless a weekend of breathing ceramic tile dust and adhesive fumes has dulled my economic senses, an upward revision of future potential oil discoveries, along with it's promise of lower future gas prices, should decrease the demand for gas today and put downward pressure on as prices, oh about, now.</p>
			<p id="p46">And another thought: might that global warming thing everyone is talking about make it easier to get to that undiscovered oil once it's discovered? Y'know, with less ice to get in the way and all. Talk about a vicious (arctic?) circle.</p>
			<p id="p47">Search</p>
			<p id="p48">-- Economic Way of Thinking</p>
			<p id="p49">-- UKNEE</p>
			<p id="p50">-- The Olive Ridley Crawl</p>
			<p id="p51">-- Mark C R UK</p>
			<p id="p52">-- American Institute of Biological Sciences</p>
			<p id="p53">-- Fritz</p>
			<p id="p54">... the Environmental Economics blog ... is now the default homepage on my browser (but then again, I guess I am a wonk -- a word I learned on the E.E. blog). That is a very nice service to the profession.</p>
			<p id="p55">-- Anonymous</p>
			<p id="p56">"... I try and read the blog everyday and have pointed it out to other faculty who have their students read it for class. It is truly one of the best things in the blogosphere."</p>
			<p id="p57">-- Anonymous</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>