<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title> Climate Politics II: Will Carbon Permits Be Even Pricier? - Environmental Capital - WSJ</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title> Climate Politics II: Will Carbon Permits Be Even Pricier? - Environmental Capital - WSJ</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-08 11:13:55.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://blogs.wsj.com/environmentalcapital/2009/03/18/climate-politics-ii-will-carbon-permits-be-even-pricier/</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/ENV_EN/9226.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Please click on the link inside the email to complete your registration</p>
			<p id="p2">Please register to gain free access to WSJ tools.</p>
			<p id="p3">An account already exists for the email address entered.</p>
			<p id="p4">The username entered is already associated with</p>
			<p id="p5">another account. Please enter a different username</p>
			<p id="p6">The email address you have entered is already in use.</p>
			<p id="p7">Please re-enter the email address.</p>
			<p id="p8">First Name</p>
			<p id="p9">Confirm Email</p>
			<p id="p10">Company Size (Optional)</p>
			<p id="p11">From time to time, we will send you e-mail announcements on new features and special offers from The Wall Street Journal Online.</p>
			<p id="p12">Create a profile for me in the Journal Community</p>
			<p id="p13">Setup and manage your portfolio</p>
			<p id="p14">Personalize your own news page</p>
			<p id="p15">Receive and manage newsletters</p>
			<p id="p16">Keep me logged in.</p>
			<p id="p17">Climate Politics II: Will Carbon Permits Be Even Pricier?</p>
			<p id="p18">By Keith Johnson</p>
			<p id="p19">The first Obama administration budget estimated that revenues from a future cap-and-trade program would total $646 billion through 2019.</p>
			<p id="p20">Well, it’ll be bigger than that (AP)</p>
			<p id="p21">Now, the WSJ reports that the White House actually expects to raise two to three times as much revenue from the climate bill. That would appear to mean that prices for emissions permits will be a lot higher than anyone is expecting—which would be both good news and bad news.</p>
			<p id="p22">Jason Furman, deputy director of the National Economic Council, told Senate staffers in late February that the plan could raise two to three times as much as the official budget figures, or between $1.3 trillion and $1.9 trillion, the WSJ reports.</p>
			<p id="p23">Now, as much as that’s exercised the folks at Planet Gore, the administration already warned that its budget figure was conservative. And it also explicitly said that any additional climate proceeds would be returned to taxpayers. So the issue isn’t what would happen with extra climate revenues.</p>
			<p id="p24">But it does seem to require a rethink of what the economic impact of the climate plan will be. Based on the figures in the budget, the price of those permits to emit greenhouse gases appeared to be between $10 and $14 a ton—all kinds of assumptions like future energy use and the pace of economic recovery make the math a little fuzzy.</p>
			<p id="p25">There seem to be only three ways to get double or triple the total climate revenues. Simply selling more permits and giving away fewer to industry for free would raise more money. The problem is that the budget already anticipates selling 100% of the emissions permits, and if anything President Obama is hinting at backing off that campaign pledge.</p>
			<p id="p26">So the climate plan could cast its net wider and cover a broader spectrum of the American economy. The more sectors that are bound to reduce emissions, and thus buy carbon permits, the bigger the revenues. The problem there is that most of the blueprints in Washington for climate legislation already talk about “economy-wide” cap-and-trade schemes—not much scope to make economy-wide even wider.</p>
			<p id="p27">That leaves carbon-emissions permits that are simply more expensive than the lowish prices that have been bandied about so far. To make the White House math work, the government would have to sell the same number of permits at prices ranging from $20 to more than $40 a ton.</p>
			<p id="p28">That would be bad news for power companies and the like that would have to buy lots of permits. Though as Geoff Styles pointed out recently, the actual energy-price impact on consumers would be quite modest—he figured a $12 permit price would raise electricity bills by about 1 cent a kilowatt hour for coal-fired plants, and gasoline by about 11 cents a gallon. Higher permit prices would mean higher energy costs, but nothing the natural-gas or gasoline spikes didn’t already do to consumers last year.</p>
			<p id="p29">But a much higher carbon price, as implied by the White House’s internal estimates, would be good news for plenty of different energy technologies, from wind and solar power to clean coal and nuclear.</p>
			<p id="p30">They all become more attractive the more expensive traditional, coal-fired and carbon-intensive power generation becomes. Clean coal, in particular, and nuclear power, to a lesser extent, need a hefty carbon price to be economically competitive.</p>
			<p id="p31">Name</p>
			<p id="p32">We welcome thoughtful comments from readers. Please comply with our guidelines . Our blogs do not require the use of your real name.</p>
			<p id="p33">Comment</p>
			<p id="p34">Peter Foley</p>
			<p id="p35">wrote:</p>
			<p id="p36">Brendan, did you read any raw data? Tree ring study? Cryosphere photos, Ice thickness in Greenland and Antarctic, Sea level rate change change? Check them out, then welcome back to reality. How did the last 30 year hiatus of cooling occour in the 40s to 70s ? and conform to simplistic models now extent?</p>
			<p id="p37">The thundering herd often is running to the chasm- Avoid the use of false threats to force silly behavior.</p>
			<p id="p38">Contrarian schools of though exist and conform to unaltered data sets.</p>
			<p id="p39">2:04 am March 26, 2009</p>
			<p id="p40">Brendan</p>
			<p id="p41">wrote:</p>
			<p id="p42">Peter, as you claim to be Mr. reality, what facts do you have to support your assertions? Any internationally recognized scnietific organizations that have published reports that conclude that the IPCC is wrong?</p>
			<p id="p43">1:09 am March 26, 2009</p>
			<p id="p44">Peter Foley</p>
			<p id="p45">wrote:</p>
			<p id="p46">The kyoto protocol is just small hint of the wealth destruction with out any change in temps the ANTI-carbon jihad will cost. the EU is abandoning the scheme as a waste of Tax Euros.</p>
			<p id="p47">CO2 emmissions have no actual cost other then lower the cost of plant producton Worldwide. They might have a politcal cost based on some religous tithes enacted by misguided governments.</p>
			<p id="p48">Only the political appointees have sold their scentific soul to the church of Anti-carbon— Where is the harm from CO2?</p>
			<p id="p49">Every day I can access the actual data and pictures of the Arctics that refute the faulty claims of the jihad, But yes there are published papers that refute AGW, Tree rings in finland perhaps, no temp increase in Antarctic after 150 years of AGW . still no winerys in England yet or swedes in Greenland growing dairy cows.</p>
			<p id="p50">Keep your “green” sprituality separate from your reality side and your life will go alot smoother.</p>
			<p id="p51">1:29 pm March 25, 2009</p>
			<p id="p52">Brendan</p>
			<p id="p53">Again with the hyperbole. You should focusing on facts rather than rants.</p>
			<p id="p54">“Brendan, Quit lying, The vast majority of the world can’t even spell climate. It’s inevitable only if Good people do nothing to stop the insanity”</p>
			<p id="p55">The Kyoto Protocol, which mandates taking action to reduce GHG emissions through emissions trading and/or other means has been ratified by 183 countries. Outside the US, There are cap and trade systems that have been implemented or proposed in most of the developed world including the EU, Swtizerland, Norway, Japan, Australia, New Zealand.</p>
			<p id="p56">“The Banks–what kind of fuzzy left wing thinking is this– ”</p>
			<p id="p57">I’m not sure what is left wing about pointing out the simple fact that banks and investors are factoring in a cost to CO2 emissions in their financial projections.</p>
			<p id="p58">As for the impact of C02, the EPA seems to have concluded otherwise. As has the IPCC</p>
			<p id="p59">“Many scams are predicated on the abuse of altruistic behavior, CO2 AGW is the greatest ever.”</p>
			<p id="p60">There is clear consensus among the world’s scientific organizations that the climate is changing due to man’s actions. Can you name one that has a published peer reviewed study that concludes otherwise? I thought not. The vast global conspiracy theory, unsupported by any facts, just doesn’t sway me.</p>
			<p id="p61">1:06 am March 25, 2009</p>
			<p id="p62">Peter Foley</p>
			<p id="p63">wrote:</p>
			<p id="p64">Brendan, Quit lying, The vast majority of the world can’t even spell climate. It’s inevitable only if Good people do nothing to stop the insanity. The Banks–what kind of fuzzy left wing thinking is this–</p>
			<p id="p65">I could try to teach you the difference between a ‘Sin’ and a crime but I have yet to master the IQ boost that you would need.</p>
			<p id="p66">Cigarettes actually harm the smokers, Creating carbon has yet to proved as a threat to society. KEEP the religous beliefs out of the government please, or immigrate to a theocracy–Iran perhaps?</p>
			<p id="p67">Many scams are predicated on the abuse of altruistic behavior, CO2 AGW is the greatest ever.</p>
			<p id="p68">About Environmental Capital</p>
			<p id="p69">Environmental Capital provides daily news and analysis of the shifting energy and environmental landscape. The Wall Street Journal’s Keith Johnson is the lead writer. Environmental Capital is led by Journal energy reporter Russell Gold, and includes contributions from other writers at the Journal, WSJ.com, and Dow Jones Newswires. Write us at environmentalcapital@wsj.com .</p>
			<p id="p70">WSJ Web Slice</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>