<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Country Summary: Gambia - Termination of Employment - Information Resources - Social Dialogue, Labour Law and Labour Administration Department</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Country Summary: Gambia - Termination of Employment - Information Resources - Social Dialogue, Labour Law and Labour Administration Department</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-20 10:38:39.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://www.ilo.org/public/english/dialogue/ifpdial/info/termination/countries/gambia.htm</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>ILO</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>OIT</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>BIT</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>International Labour Organization</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/LAB_EN/118.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Information last updated 2000.</p>
			<p id="p2">Sources of regulation</p>
			<p id="p3">The Labour Act, 1990 (LA), is the major source of law in Gambia in relation to termination of employment at the initiative of the employer.</p>
			<p id="p4">Scope of legislation</p>
			<p id="p5">The following categories of workers are excluded from all of the provisions of the LA: civil servants, members of the naval, military, prison and security services, police officers and domestic workers (sec. 2(2), LA).</p>
			<p id="p6">The following workers are excluded from the provision of the LA dealing with termination of employment: any employee over 55 who has reached a contractual retirement age; any employee over 65; a probationary employee; and any employee whose dismissal is certified as being in accordance with the national interest by the Secretary of the Cabinet.</p>
			<p id="p7">Contracts of employment</p>
			<p id="p8">Contracts of employment may be for a fixed term or for an indefinite period. A fixed-term contract will expire on the specific date indicated in the contract or when the specific task, piece of work or journey to which the contract relates has been finished (sec. 83, LA). However, if the specific period, task, piece of work or journey expires or is performed, but the employment continues without protest for four weeks thereafter, the contract is deemed to have been immediately renewed for an indefinite period (sec. 83(4), LA). Probationary periods are permissible, but may not exceed six months.</p>
			<p id="p9">Termination of employment</p>
			<p id="p10">The contract of employment can terminate, not at the initiative of the employer, in certain circumstances, including by:</p>
			<p id="p11">employee retirement;</p>
			<p id="p12">the completion of the task for which the contract was concluded.</p>
			<p id="p13">Moreover, unless the contract expressly provides to the contrary, the death of the employer will cause the contract of employment to terminate after one month from the date of such death, unless the contract has been lawfully terminated sooner. The personal representative of the deceased shall be deemed to be the employer during such time as the contract continues (sec. 80, LA). [1]</p>
			<p id="p14">According to sec. 80(2) of the LA, the compulsory winding-up of any company or organization shall operate to terminate any contract of employment with that company or organization, but shall not prevent renewal of that contract by the receiver or other person carrying on the business of the company or organization. If such contract is renewed within two months of such termination, it shall be deemed not to have been terminated.</p>
			<p id="p15">Where a trade or business is transferred in whole or in part, save by a receiver upon the insolvency of the business, [2] the contracts of employment of all employees at the date of transfer shall automatically be transferred to the transferee and all rights and obligations between the employer and the transferor shall continue to apply as if they had been rights and obligations between the employee and the transferee (sec. 74(2), LA).</p>
			<p id="p16">Dismissal</p>
			<p id="p17">An employer is required to justify a dismissal of his or her employee. Dismissal will be justified in cases of incapacity or misconduct, such as:</p>
			<p id="p18">wilful misconduct;</p>
			<p id="p19">omission or disobedience by the worker which, by its nature and the circumstances in which it occurs, is such that no reasonable employer would expect the employment to continue;</p>
			<p id="p20">serious or persistent insubordination;</p>
			<p id="p21">incompetence;</p>
			<p id="p22">a single long period of absence without substantial reason;</p>
			<p id="p23">unreasonable refusal to accept other suitable employment in cases where the enterprise needs such redeployment; or</p>
			<p id="p24">wilful destruction or obstruction of safety equipment available for use (sec. 116, LA).</p>
			<p id="p25">Summary dismissal is allowed in the following circumstances:</p>
			<p id="p26">when the employee is guilty of serious misconduct;</p>
			<p id="p27">where, within three months of engagement, the employer has reasonable grounds to believe that the employee lacks the skill or ability which he or she has represented himself or herself to possess and which the law requires should be possessed by an employee for performing the specified work; or</p>
			<p id="p28">where the contract of employment is void for misrepresentation (sec. 112, LA).</p>
			<p id="p29">Where the employer does not provide reasons for dismissal when requested by the employee, such dismissal is deemed unfair (sec. 114(1), LA). Where such a dismissal takes place before completion of any period wherein wages become due, the employee shall be paid a proportionate part of the wages then due (sec. 112(2), LA).</p>
			<p id="p30">Under sec. 117 of the LA, the following constitute invalid reasons for dismissal:</p>
			<p id="p31">pregnancy;</p>
			<p id="p32">the fact that the employee has taken maternity leave;</p>
			<p id="p33">participation in trade union activities, including the organization of lawful industrial action outside working hours or, with the express consent of the employer, within working hours;</p>
			<p id="p34">membership of a trade union; </p>
			<p id="p35">refusal or indication of an intention to refuse to join any organization of workers;</p>
			<p id="p36">a period of absence by reason of illness or injury of less than two weeks unless the employee, on the reasonable request of the employer, fails to supply reasonable independent evidence that he or she was incapacitated for the whole period;</p>
			<p id="p37">instigation by the police of investigations involving the employee concerning a matter not connected with suitability of the employee for a particular employment;</p>
			<p id="p38">a single instance of absenteeism, not being a long unexplained absence so as to justify summary dismissal;</p>
			<p id="p39">taking of steps by the employee to enforce any right granted or any obligation imposed upon the employer;</p>
			<p id="p40">refusal by the employee in any circumstances, save those of grave national emergency or of grave emergency applicable to the employer, to work for more than the number of hours permitted by any rule of law or international convention;</p>
			<p id="p41">any political activity engaged in or political opinion expressed by the employee; and</p>
			<p id="p42">the dismissal of an apprentice, unless the dismissal is necessitated by personal injury or wilful act by the apprentice, or the employer is going out of business.</p>
			<p id="p43">When collective dismissal is being considered, the employer has to provide the relevant trade unions with written information concerning the circumstances giving rise to the need for dismissal, possible alternative options and whether they are feasible, whether redeployment or retraining has been considered, whether it is reasonably possible that a certain number of employees might be re-employed during the next year, and the principles which will be taken into account when deciding on whom to dismiss (such as “last in, first out”). The employer must then consult with relevant trade unions (sec. 119, LA).</p>
			<p id="p44">The provisions governing collective dismissal shall not apply to employers with five or less employees in all his or her establishments, or where a collective agreement governs the conditions of collective dismissal (sec. 119(3), LA).</p>
			<p id="p45">Notice and prior procedural safeguards</p>
			<p id="p46">Notice is mandatory for all cases of dismissal except summary dismissal. In cases where it is customary to employ individuals on a day-to-day basis, notice shall be given at the end of the day (sec. 111(1)(a), LA). This notice shall be deemed to have been given by specifying that the contract will last for one (additional) day only. For all others, notice periods are as follows:</p>
			<p id="p47">in the case of an employee not employed on a day-to-day basis, but who has been employed for less than one week’s continuous employment with the same employer, 24 hours’ notice (sec. 111(1)(b), LA);</p>
			<p id="p48">in the case of an employee with one week or more of continuous employment but less than six months’ continuous employment with the same employer, one week’s notice (sec. 111(1)(d), LA);</p>
			<p id="p49">in the case of an employee with six months or more but less than six years of continuous employment with the same employer, one month’s notice (sec. 111(1)(c) and (e), LA); and</p>
			<p id="p50">in the case of an employee with six years or more of continuous employment with the same employer, two months’ notice (sec. 111(1)(f), LA). </p>
			<p id="p51">Under sec. 109, requirements for notice are excluded in the cases of:</p>
			<p id="p52">any employee who has attained the age fixed for retirement in accordance with sec. 90 [3] or the age of 65 years, whichever is earlier;</p>
			<p id="p53">termination of the employment relationship during the probation period;</p>
			<p id="p54">any employee whose dismissal is certified by the Secretary of the Cabinet as being in the national interest;</p>
			<p id="p55">a summary dismissal;</p>
			<p id="p56">the payment of wages in lieu of notice (that is, a sum equivalent to the basic wage payable for the period of notice (sec. 111, LA); and</p>
			<p id="p57">for fixed-term employees, provided that the contract has not been renewed immediately after expiration. [4]</p>
			<p id="p58">Before dismissal takes place, the employee has to be informed about the reasons for dismissal and has to be given a reasonable chance to respond (sec. 113, LA). The dismissed employee has the right to approach the Industrial Tribunal (sec. 121, LA). Such an employee also has the right to be represented by a trade union representative (sec. 113, LA). Where the employer does not comply with these conditions, it will constitute an unfair dismissal, unless the employer can prove that the employee was aware of these rights (sec. 113(3) and (4), LA). The Industrial Tribunal has jurisdiction over dismissal disputes (sec. 21(2), LA). Any party who is aggrieved by a decision may appeal to the Supreme Court whose decision is final (sec. 43(1), LA).</p>
			<p id="p59">Severance pay</p>
			<p id="p60">In the case of summary dismissal, the employee must be paid any remuneration or benefits accruing to him or her up until the date of the dismissal (sec. 112(2), LA).</p>
			<p id="p61">Avenues for redress</p>
			<p id="p62">The Industrial Labour Tribunal has jurisdiction over all types of dismissal claims (sec. 112, LA). Claims can be filed with the Industrial Tribunal within six months from the date of dismissal. The burden of proof rests with the employer (sec. 115, LA). Where the employer cannot prove the reasons for dismissal, such dismissal will be deemed unfair. In cases where no settlement is reached by the parties, the Industrial Tribunal has jurisdiction to order reinstatement or compensation or both. The Industrial Tribunal has the power to award such compensation as it considers just and equitable, although this amount can be reduced by reason of the conduct of the employee in contributing to his or her dismissal or in failing to mitigate the loss he or she has suffered (sec. 123, LA). According to sec. 123(3), the court will also consider, inter alia, other job opportunities available, the value of contractual benefits to which the employee might reasonably have expected to become entitled to had he or she not been dismissed; and the value of statutory rights such as pensions or other accrued benefits.</p>
			<p id="p63">Further information</p>
			<p id="p64">[2] The transferee will, in these circumstances, not be liable for the debts of the insolvent undertaking.</p>
			<p id="p65">[3] Sec. 90 stipulates that a term in a contract of employment, fixing a retirement age for an employee at any age after reaching his or her 55th birthday, shall be valid and enforceable, and termination in accordance with such provision shall not amount to a dismissal.</p>
			<p id="p66">[4] It thus seems that the premature termination of a fixed-term contract would also not require notice.</p>
			<p id="p67">Employment protection legislation database - EPLex</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>