<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>&#xd;
	Healthcare Around The World: How Do We Stack Up? - An Everyday Health Special Feature&#xd;
</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>&#xd;
	Healthcare Around The World: How Do We Stack Up? - An Everyday Health Special Feature&#xd;
</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-20 10:39:42.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://www.everydayhealth.com/features/healthcare/comparison-sidebar.aspx</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>health care</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>insurance</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>coverage</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>socialized medicine</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>HMO</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>PPO</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>maternity leave</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>SiCKO</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>Michael Moore</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/LAB_EN/191.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">How Does Your Coverage Measure Up?</p>
			<p id="p2">Check out the medical and maternity benefits citizens receive in various countries. The differences may surprise you!</p>
			<p id="p3">By Adrienne Rayski</p>
			<p id="p4">United States</p>
			<p id="p5">Medical Benefits: Healthcare in the U.S. is provided by private entities commonly called Health Maintenance Organizations (HMOs) or Preferred Provider Organizations (PPOs). Most citizens receive health insurance through their employers, but insurance can also be purchased by individuals. Approximately 47 million Americans are without medical coverage, according to The U.S. Census Bureau . A few government programs exist to provide health care for the poor and elderly — the largest being Medicaid. According to the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, "Medicaid is available only to certain low-income individuals and families who fit into an eligibility group recognized by federal and state law. Medicaid does not pay money to you; instead, it sends payments directly to your health care providers." Medicaid also offers prescription drug coverage, but enlisters are required to pay a monthly premium. Those who do not have medical insurance at all and are ineligible for Medicaid must pay medical fees out of pocket.</p>
			<p id="p6">Maternity Benefits: Employers are required to grant new mothers up to 12 weeks of unpaid leave with job security under the Family and Medical Leave Act. Many employers, however, have their own policies on maternity leave and do offer pay for a portion of this time. The average cost of a hospital stay for childbirth in the United States is $8,800, according to a study conducted by The March of Dimes .</p>
			<p id="p7">France</p>
			<p id="p8">Medical Benefits: French residents are covered by public health insurance, which is part in parcel of the French social security entitlement program. This public health insurance also helps cover the cost of prescription drugs. According to the National Coalition on Health Care , coverage is provided through a combination of employer/employee contributions and personal income taxes. Poor citizens (those making less than 6,000 euros a year — approximately $8000) are not required to pay this tax. Public health insurance may not cover the total cost of specialist visits, in-home visits, or weekend/holiday visits; additional health insurance coverage is available for purchase by French citizens who wish to do so.</p>
			<p id="p9">Maternity Benefits: Women in France take 16 weeks of mandatory, paid maternity leave from work, according to the BBC . This time allotment increases after the woman has had a second child. Both men and women have the option to take up to three years off from work (unpaid) after having a child, with total job security if he or she decides to return to work. The French government also offers citizens a host of parental services, including financial supplements for families with three or more children, single parent allowances, low-cost day care and nanny services.</p>
			<p id="p10">England</p>
			<p id="p11">Medical Benefits: National health care in England is provided by the British National Health Service (NHS). Citizens may choose their own doctors or can visit an NHS Walk-in Center, where no appointments are necessary, for minor health problems. The NHS also helps to pay for dental care, opticians, medical equipment and prescription drugs. A recent initiative now rewards doctors with increased pay for helping patients to take preventative health measures, such as quitting smoking.</p>
			<p id="p12">Maternity Benefits: In England, women on maternity leave are entitled to 26 weeks off at full pay (90 percent from the government and the rest by the employer), according to the BBC. New fathers can take up to two weeks paid paternity leave. Other benefits to parents in England include tax breaks, the ability to create flexible work schedules and parental leave with job security.</p>
			<p id="p13">Canada</p>
			<p id="p14">Medical Benefits: Canada's national health care system is provided through public funding and maintained by the government. Visits to specialists, dental treatment, and prescription drugs are not covered by Canadian national health care, but additional health insurance can be purchased to help cover these costs. Private clinics, which charge patients for services, also exist in Canada. According to Canadian-Healthcare.org , "Private clinics typically offer services with reduced wait times compared to the public health care system. For example, obtaining an MRI scan in a hospital could require a waiting period of months, whereas it could be obtained much faster in a private clinic. Private clinics are a subject of controversy, as some feel that their existence unbalances the health care system and favors treatments to those with higher incomes."</p>
			<p id="p15">Maternity Benefits: Women who work at least 600 hours in the previous year may receive up to 15 weeks of paid maternity leave, according to Service Canada . New parents — including those of adopted children — are eligible for financial allowances from the government.</p>
			<p id="p16">Cuba</p>
			<p id="p17">Medical Benefits: The Cuban government maintains a public healthcare system; private hospitals and doctor's offices are prohibited. Citizens capable of paying for prescription drugs, dental, and medical equipment, such as wheelchairs, do so. Low income patients are provided with these services by the government. Cuban medicine's focus is on preventative treatment rather than treatment of the sick. According to the U.S. Department of State, the U.S. trade embargo on Cuba has, however, made it difficult for the country to provide prescription drugs of an equally high quality to its citizens.</p>
			<p id="p18">Maternity Benefits: The Medical Education Cooperation with Cuba (MEDICC) states that, "Women are entitled to 18 weeks fully-paid leave (six weeks before birth and 12 after), plus an additional 40 weeks at 60 percent pay, assured of returning to their same job." Both father and mother have the option to take paid leave at 60 percent of their salaries to care for their infants from the age of 12 weeks up to one year of age. Fathers may take this leave regardless of whether the couple is married or not.</p>
			<p id="p19">This section created and produced exclusively by the editorial staff of EverydayHealth.com. © 2009 EverydayHealth.com; all rights reserved.</p>
			<p id="p20">Everyday Solutions</p>
			<p id="p21">Advertising Notice</p>
			<p id="p22">This Site and third parties who place advertisements on this Site may collect and use information about your visits to this Site and other websites in order to provide advertisements about goods and services of interest to you. If you would like to obtain more information about these advertising practices and to make choices about online behavioral advertising, please click here</p>
			<p id="p23">The material on this web site is provided for educational purposes only, and is not to be used for medical advice, diagnosis or treatment. See additional information . Use of this site is subject to our terms of use and privacy policy .</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>