<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>parental leave: Definition from Answers.com</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>parental leave: Definition from Answers.com</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-20 11:04:02.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://www.answers.com/topic/parental-leave</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>parental leave</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>Definition</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>reference</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/LAB_EN/1968.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">n.</p>
			<p id="p2">"Maternity leave" redirects here. For the episode of Lost, see Maternity Leave (Lost) .</p>
			<p id="p3">Parental leave is an employee benefit that provides paid or unpaid time off work to care for a child or make arrangements for the child's welfare. Often, the term parental leave includes maternity , paternity , and adoption leave. Often the minimum benefits are stipulated by law.</p>
			<p id="p4">Contents</p>
			<p id="p5">Variation in International Law</p>
			<p id="p6">In most countries, paid parental leave (typically maternity leave) is available for those who have worked for their current employer for a certain period of time. [1] National legislations vary widely as it is a matter of politics to decide the appropriate type of parental leave legislation. The United States is the only Western country that does not mandate paid parental leave, although the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 mandates unpaid parental leave for the majority of American workers.</p>
			<p id="p7">Legal requirements for parental leave benefits do not always reflect actual practice. In some countries with relatively weak requirements, individual employers choose to provide benefits beyond those required by law. In some countries, laws requiring parental leave benefits are widely ignored in practice.[ citation needed ]</p>
			<p id="p8">Benefits in a selection of countries</p>
			<p id="p9">A large majority of countries provide more than 10 paid weeks maternity leave. Only four provide none.</p>
			<p id="p10">Histogram of Paid Leave by country.</p>
			<p id="p11">When entries are not listed in the subsection tables, it may be because they are unknown and not that they do not exist. [2] [3]</p>
			<p id="p12">Europe</p>
			<p id="p13">Central European countries are the most dedicated countries in the world regarding parental leave. In Czech Republic , it is standard that mothers stay at home for 3 years with every child. All mothers can decide to take 2, 3 or 4 years of maternity leave. It is also possible for the fathers to take the leave instead of the mothers but it is not common. For the whole period mothers are supported by the state. Similar model is also used in Austria where mothers can choose between 1 and 3 years. Also in Slovakia , standard duration of parental leave is 3 years, for handicapped child it is up to 6 years. State pays support 256 Euros per month for the first 2 years of age of the child. After this period it is 164.22 Euros per month.</p>
			<p id="p14">Sweden is one country which provides generous parental leave: all working parents are entitled to 16 months paid leave per child, the cost being shared between employer and the state. To encourage greater paternal involvement in child-rearing, a minimum of 2 months out of the 16 is required to be used by the "minority" parent, in practice usually the father, and some Swedish political parties on the political left argue for legislation to oblige families to divide the 16 months equally between both parents. [4] Norway also has similarly generous leave. In Estonia mothers are entitled to 18 months of paid leave, starting up to 70 days before due date. Fathers are entitled to paid leave starting from the third month after birth (paid leave is however available to only one parent at a time).</p>
			<p id="p15">In the UK , all female employees are entitled to 52 weeks of maternity (or adoption) leave, 39 weeks of which is paid, rising to 52 weeks paid from April 2010, with the first six weeks paid at 90% of full pay and the remainder at a fixed rate. Most employers offer a more generous policy. Annual leave continues to accrue throughout the maternity leave period. A spouse or partner of the woman (including same-sex relationships) may request a two week paid (at a fixed rate) paternity leave. [5] Both the mother and her partner can additionally request non-paid parental leave, which can be for up to 4 weeks annually, with a current limit of 13 weeks. [6]</p>
			<p id="p16">62%</p>
			<p id="p17">31%</p>
			<p id="p18">between 1 and 3 years depending on chosen payment ( percentage of last income for one year; ca. €436/month for three years)</p>
			<p id="p19">77%</p>
			<p id="p20">7 days but 82% paid out by health insurance fund</p>
			<p id="p21">130%</p>
			<p id="p22">6 months to be used until the child turns 8</p>
			<p id="p23">6 months to be used until the child turns 8</p>
			<p id="p24">28 weeks (6-8 weeks before birth) ~70%; &amp; parental leave up to 2/3/4 years of age of the child (approx. 633/422/211$ a month). Can be taken by either of the parents or by both at the same time (but only one will receive the monetary support).</p>
			<p id="p25">38%</p>
			<p id="p26">100%</p>
			<p id="p27">38%</p>
			<p id="p28">3 years</p>
			<p id="p29">58%</p>
			<p id="p30">Until child turns 3</p>
			<p id="p31">31%</p>
			<p id="p32">Share of 104 weeks (2 years) with father</p>
			<p id="p33">Share of 104 weeks (2 years) with mother</p>
			<p id="p34">84%</p>
			<p id="p35">Share of 156 weeks (3 years) with father</p>
			<p id="p36">Share of 156 weeks (3 years) with mother</p>
			<p id="p37">Must have private health insurance for part of paid leave, rest of paid leave paid by employer</p>
			<p id="p38">90 days 80% (based on total salary over a 12 month period ending 6 months before the birth). Max. monthly payment for 2008: Íkr535,700 (around €4,500, $6,500 at exchange rates in August 2008); min. monthly payment for 2008: Íkr103,869 (around €870, $1,250)</p>
			<p id="p39">+ 90 days to be shared freely between the parents [8]</p>
			<p id="p40">39%</p>
			<p id="p41">13 weeks</p>
			<p id="p42">Parents must have been working for a period of 6 months prior to taking the leave. Parental leave can be taken at any time during the first 18 months of the baby's life.</p>
			<p id="p43">50%</p>
			<p id="p44">16 (4 months) weeks that can be shared with mother</p>
			<p id="p45">34%</p>
			<p id="p46">Maximum 26 weeks (6 months) (total for both parents maximum 44 weeks (10 months))</p>
			<p id="p47">Maximum 30 weeks (7 months) (total for both parents maximum 44 weeks (10 months))</p>
			<p id="p48">For paid leave, job contract must include social contributions (INPS)</p>
			<p id="p49">185%</p>
			<p id="p50">26 weeks</p>
			<p id="p51">Unpaid leave for children under 8. For unpaid leave you have to have worked for an employer for over 1 year. The government gives all parents that use unpaid parental leave, through tax breaks, 50% of the national minimum wage. Employers have the possibility to provide a payment on their own discretion. Payment for parental leave can also be set at the collective labour agreements.</p>
			<p id="p52">56 weeks (13 months) (80%) or 46 weeks (10.5 months) (100%) - mother must take at least 3 weeks immediately before birth and 6 weeks immediately after birth, father must take at least 10 weeks - the rest can be shared between mother and father.</p>
			<p id="p53">86%</p>
			<p id="p54">10 weeks of the 56/46 weeks paid leave is reserved for the father. If he does not take these 10 weeks, they will be lost as they can not be transferred to the mother.</p>
			<p id="p55">The mother can also take an extra full year of unpaid leave after the paid period ends.</p>
			<p id="p56">The father can also take an extra full year of unpaid leave after the paid period ends. In addition, the father is entitled to take two weeks unpaid leave directly before or after birth (many fathers are paid for these weeks by their employers).</p>
			<p id="p57">To gain the right to paid leave for herself and the father, the mother must have worked for 6 of the last 10 months before birth, or the leave is unpaid (except for a lump sum benefit from the government)</p>
			<p id="p58">up to 3 years, may be splitted</p>
			<p id="p59">33%</p>
			<p id="p60">Five days plus two weeks.</p>
			<p id="p61">Of the maternity leave, 6 weeks is compulsory. The father may take the rest of the time the mother would have been entitled to.</p>
			<p id="p62">29%</p>
			<p id="p63">Five days plus 10 more days if the father has taken a child care course (these 10 days are given only once, so not for every child). All 15 days must be taken within the first 8 weeks since the birth of the baby.</p>
			<p id="p64">Must have worked 12 months in the previous year.</p>
			<p id="p65">140-194 days (before birth: 70 days, or 84 days if multiple pregnancy; after birth: 70 days, or 86 days in case of complications, or 110 days if multiple birth) [9] 100%;</p>
			<p id="p66">followed by: up to 18 months after birth - 1,500-6,000 RUB for the first child, 3,000-6,000 RUB for any subsequent child, but not exceeding 100% [10] (could be shared with father, grandparents, guardians or actual caregivers of the child).</p>
			<p id="p67">53%</p>
			<p id="p68">following the after-birth portion of maternity leave, up to 18 months after birth - 1,500-6,000 RUB a month for the first child, 3,000-6,000 RUB a month for any subsequent child, but not exceeding 100% (could be shared with father, grandparents, guardians or actual caregivers of the child)</p>
			<p id="p69">up to 18 months (1.5–3 years after birth), could be shared with father, grandparents, guardians or actual caregivers of the child</p>
			<p id="p70">up to 18 months (1.5–3 years after birth), could be shared with mother, grandparents, guardians or actual caregivers of the child</p>
			<p id="p71">31%</p>
			<p id="p72">15 days (in the next years 30 days), independently of the mother. Up to 15 days of the mother's leave can be taken by the father (if the father takes all 15 days, the mother only has 97 days to take off instead of the full 4 weeks (112 days))</p>
			<p id="p73">Up to 3 years.</p>
			<p id="p74">2,500 € for every baby. 100 €/month for mother that worked. No free public day-care center from 0 to 3 years old infants. ABOLISHED FROM 1st JANUARY 2011.</p>
			<p id="p75">82%</p>
			<p id="p76">480 days (16 months) (62.08% (80% of 80% of 97%) up to a ceiling the first 390 days, 90 days at flat rate) - shared with mother (dedicated 60 days) + 10 working days in connection with the child's birth</p>
			<p id="p77">The first 18 months (at maximum) individually, by postponing the shared paid period.</p>
			<p id="p78">The first 18 months (at maximum) individually, by postponing the shared paid period.</p>
			<p id="p79">31%</p>
			<p id="p80">6 months</p>
			<p id="p81">Currently 39 weeks paid, due to rise to 52 weeks paid from April 2010, although delayed indefinitely [11] (6 weeks at 90% of full pay and remainder at a flat rate (as of 2009 = £123.06) or 90% of your salary if that is less than the flat rate). This is the statutory minimum; most employers often provide more generous arrangements.</p>
			<p id="p82">10.3% + flat rate of £123.06/week after week 6</p>
			<p id="p83">2 weeks at a fixed amount (as of March 2009 = £123.06)</p>
			<p id="p84">4 weeks per year (non-paid and a max of 13 weeks) via a Parental leave request if they have at least one year's continuous employment</p>
			<p id="p85">13 weeks unpaid(maternity or adoption) for total a of 52 weeks (paid and non-paid)</p>
			<p id="p86">4 weeks per year (non-paid and a max of 13 weeks) via a Parental leave request if they have at least one year's continuous employment</p>
			<p id="p87">None. Though note that a spouse or partner can request up to 4 weeks non-paid Parental leave annually (max 13 weeks) if they have at least one year's continuous employment</p>
			<p id="p88">The person requesting Maternity/Adoption or Paternity leave person must have worked for their current employer for at least 26 weeks before the 15th week before the due date (and received a salary that is higher than a fixed minimum). They must give the employer notice before the 15th week before the child is due.</p>
			<p id="p89">Americas</p>
			<p id="p90">In 2000, parental leave was greatly expanded in Canada from 10 weeks to 35 weeks divided as desired between two parents. This is in addition to 15 weeks maternity leave. In most situations, a combination of maternity and parental benefits can be received up to a combined maximum of 50 weeks. In Canada maternity and parental leave is paid for by the Employment Insurance system. [12]</p>
			<p id="p91">5 days (Article 10, Paragraph 1, of Temporary Constitutional Provisions Act of Brazilian Constitution) [3]</p>
			<p id="p92">55% up to $447/week for 35 weeks parental leave (shared with mother) [14]</p>
			<p id="p93">2 weeks</p>
			<p id="p94">Quebec, 70% up to $834.61/week for 25 weeks, then 55% up to $655.76/week for 25 weeks. As with the federal plan, there are 32 weeks of parental leave that can be shared with father. In addition, fathers are eligible for 5 weeks paid leave at a rate of up to 70% of their income or 3 weeks paid leave at a rate of 75% of their income.</p>
			<p id="p95">18 weeks 100% (with a cup)</p>
			<p id="p96">Article 66 indicates 1 day paid; Law N° 20.047 (2005) increased paternity leave to 4 days paid leave. (edward gonzalez-acosta, The New School)</p>
			<p id="p97">12 weeks 100%</p>
			<p id="p98">Law 755 (2002) appended a paragraph to Article 236 of the Labor Code to indicate that fathers have a leave of 4–8 days. (edward gonzalez-acosta, The New School)</p>
			<p id="p99">Two days</p>
			<p id="p100">Must work for a covered employer (all public agencies; private companies with 50 or more employees within 75 miles.)</p>
			<p id="p101">Must have worked for covered employer for at least 12 months prior, and at least 1250 hours in previous 12 months. Other restrictions apply.</p>
			<p id="p102">10 days family-related leave</p>
			<p id="p103">Five days of unpaid leave in the event of exceptional or serious events</p>
			<p id="p104">10 days</p>
			<p id="p105">Four days of paid leave for "compassionate reasons"</p>
			<p id="p106">Three days paid family responsibility leave</p>
			<p id="p107">1 day (private sector), 2 days (public sector)</p>
			<p id="p108">4 working days 100%</p>
			<p id="p109">Paid maternity leave may only be taken once every 36 months</p>
			<p id="p110">Asia/Pacific</p>
			<p id="p111">Australia will be introducing an 18 week paid maternity leave scheme starting in 2011. It is to be publicly funded, and to provide the federal minimum wage (currently AUS $543.78 a week) rather than a percentage of the primary caregiver's salary. It will not be available to families wherein the primary caregiver has an annual salary above $150,000. [15]</p>
			<p id="p112">From January 1, 2011, 18 weeks at federal minimum wage is provided.</p>
			<p id="p113">Up to 52 weeks unpaid shared with father.</p>
			<p id="p114">Up to 1 week unpaid taken at time of birth. Up to an additional 51 weeks if not taken at the same time as the mother, and for the purposes of providing primary care. Employer has right to refuse.</p>
			<p id="p115">The 52 weeks are shared between the parents, and all leave must be completed before the child's first birthday.</p>
			<p id="p116">In case of third (+) time mom, who has two or more babies alive already.</p>
			<p id="p117">12 weeks 100%</p>
			<p id="p118">Does not apply to the state of Jammu and Kashmir . [16] Prohibits employers from allowing women to work within six weeks of giving birth. [17] A female employee is eligible only if she worked for the employer at least 80 days during the 12-month period preceding the date of expected delivery. [18] In the case of a stillbirth or miscarriage, six weeks of paid leave is required instead. [18] Female employees of the Central Government of India receive 180 days of leave. [19]</p>
			<p id="p119">14 weeks 100%. The weeks from 6th to 14th can be taken by the father.</p>
			<p id="p120">Can take the paid leave instead of the mother starting from the 6th week (up to 14 weeks)</p>
			<p id="p121">1 year</p>
			<p id="p122">1 year</p>
			<p id="p123">When parents take turns, the total period may be extended 2 months (but no longer than 1 year for each parent). [20]</p>
			<p id="p124">1 year (400US$ per a month paid by Employment Insurance)until the child is 3 years old</p>
			<p id="p125">1 year (400US$ per a month paid by Employment Insurance)until the child is 3 years old</p>
			<p id="p126">12 weeks 66.7%</p>
			<p id="p127">Six days of "casual leave" that can be used by fathers to assist their spouses at the time of confinement</p>
			<p id="p128">38 weeks</p>
			<p id="p129">One day</p>
			<p id="p130">16 weeks 100%</p>
			<p id="p131">Leave is restricted to married women whose children are Singapore citizens (at least one parent is a Singapore citizen)</p>
			<p id="p132">International organizations</p>
			<p id="p133">As international organizations are not subject to the legislation of any country, they have their own internal legislation on parental leave.</p>
			<p id="p134">Organization</p>
			<p id="p135">16 weeks 100% (however, no fewer than 10 weeks must be after delivery, even if the pre-delivery leave was longer due to a late birth)</p>
			<p id="p136">4 weeks 100% (or 8 weeks for staff members serving at locations where they are not allowed to live with their family)</p>
			<p id="p137">The fact that a staff member is or will be on parental leave cannot be a factor in deciding contract renewal. To ensure that this is enforced, if a contract ends while the staff member is on parental leave, the contract must be extended to cover the duration of such leave.</p>
			<p id="p138">See also</p>
			<p id="p139">Notes</p>
			<p id="p140">^ a b Department of Business Enterprise &amp; Regulation (2007)(ed.): Internal Review of Leave Policies and Related Research 2007, in: Employment Relations Research Series No. 80, p. 96, URL: http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file40677.pdf</p>
			<p id="p141">^ The paternal leave rights are compiled from the International Labour Organization site at http://www.ilo.org/public/english/protection/condtrav/family/reconcilwf/specialleave.htm copyrighted 2006. This site does not list the amount paid for paid leave. Where information from the International Labour Organization disagreed with http://ec.europa.eu/eures/home.jsp?lang=en , the EU site has been given precedence</p>
			<p id="p142">^ Updated September 2008, from http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/products/indwm/ww2005/tab5c.htm</p>
			<p id="p143">^ Information on Swedish parental leave from http://www.forsakringskassan.se/</p>
			<p id="p144">External links</p>
			<p id="p145">BBC article on proposed parental leave in Germany designed to halt the decline in the birth rate and male/female workplace inequality - http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4852040.stm</p>
			<p id="p146">BBC article on declining birth rate in Italy - http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4739154.stm</p>
			<p id="p147">BBC article on declining birth rate in Poland and new schemes designed to increase it - http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4852924.stm</p>
			<p id="p148">BBC article on success of Norway's parental leave scheme - http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4786160.stm</p>
			<p id="p149">BBC guide to parenthood policies in Europe - http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4837422.stm (n.b. In this BBC article parental leave means unpaid leave)</p>
			<p id="p150">Trends in Maternity Leave for First-Time Mothers in the U.S. - http://fycs.ifas.ufl.edu/news/2006/05/family-album-radio-trends-in-maternity.html</p>
			<p id="p151">TUC page about maternity rights in the UK - http://www.worksmart.org.uk/rights/what_time_off_work_am_i_entitled</p>
			<p id="p152">Center for Law and Social Policy on need for reform in the US: http://www.clasp.org/publications/getting_punched_fullnotes.pdf</p>
			<p id="p153">Canadian Labour Standards Government website - http://www.hrsdc.gc.ca/en/lp/spila/wlb/wppp/02leave_benefits.shtml</p>
			<p id="p154">Attendance</p>
			<p id="p155">Copyrights:</p>
			<p id="p156">Dictionary. The American Heritage® Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition Copyright © 2007, 2000 by Houghton Mifflin Company. Updated in 2009. Published by Houghton Mifflin Company. All rights reserved. Read more</p>
			<p id="p157">Wikipedia. This article is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution/Share-Alike License. It uses material from the Wikipedia article Parental leave. Read more</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>