<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Country Summary: Switzerland - Termination of Employment - Information Resources - Social Dialogue, Labour Law and Labour Administration Department</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Country Summary: Switzerland - Termination of Employment - Information Resources - Social Dialogue, Labour Law and Labour Administration Department</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-20 10:40:01.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://www.ilo.org/public/english/dialogue/ifpdial/info/termination/countries/switzerland.htm</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>ILO</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>OIT</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>BIT</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>International Labour Organization</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/LAB_EN/210.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Updated in January 2007 by Ms Angelika Muller, ILO.</p>
			<p id="p2">Sources of regulation</p>
			<p id="p3">The sources of labour law are to be found in the Code of Obligations (CO) of 30 March 1911, as amended in July 2006, Part X of which is entitled “Contracts of Employment”, [1] and the federal Labour Act (LA) concerning work in industry, handicrafts and commerce of 13 March 1964, as amended by several ordinances. In addition, labour law is governed by, among others, collective contracts of employment (CCE), which can be either national or cantonal.</p>
			<p id="p4">Scope of legislation</p>
			<p id="p5">The CO applies to every contract of private law and regulates the employment relationship between employers and workers who conclude individual employment contracts.</p>
			<p id="p6">According to Art. 320 of the CO, employment contracts do not require for their validity any special form. However, when the duration of employment relationship is unlimited or of more than one month, the employer must inform by written the worker on specified work conditions (Art. 330b CO), such as the name of the parties, date of the beginning of the employment relationship, job description, salary conditions and weekly number of work hours.</p>
			<p id="p7">Written contracts are considered mandatory in the case of some special contracts, such as those made for apprentices (Art. 344a (1) CO) and travelling sales staff (Art. 347a (1) CO).</p>
			<p id="p8">Contracts of employment</p>
			<p id="p9">Art. 319 CO stipulates that under an individual employment contract the worker undertakes to perform work in the employer’s service for either a fixed or an indefinite period of time and the employer is obliged to pay wages based either on time periods, or on the work performed (time wage or piece-work wage). The concept of an employment contract also includes contracts whereby the employee undertakes to regularly perform work in the employer’s service on an hourly, half-day or daily basis (part-time work).</p>
			<p id="p10">The duration of the employment contract is set by agreement of the parties. It is indefinite, except where a fixed term has been agreed by the parties or is dictated by the nature of the work. Fixed-term contracts terminate with the expiry of the agreed period. If a fixed-term contract is tacitly renewed, it is deemed concluded for indefinite duration (Art. 334, CO). However, a fixed-term agreement intended to circumvent the terms and conditions of dismissal prescribed by law is void.</p>
			<p id="p11">Termination of employment</p>
			<p id="p12">The Swiss legislation on the termination of employment relationship applies in principle equally to the employer and the worker. A contract concluded for an indefitite period can be terminated after a period of notice given by one of the parties or at any time, without prior notice, if one of the parties has a just cause to terminate it.</p>
			<p id="p13">The contract of employment can be terminated, not at the initiative of the employer, in certain circumstances, including by:</p>
			<p id="p14">the expiry of an employment relationship for a fixed term;</p>
			<p id="p15">notice from the employee; and</p>
			<p id="p16">the death of the employer; however, the employee may claim reasonable compensation for damage caused to him or her because of the premature ending of the employment relationship (Art. 338a(2), CO).</p>
			<p id="p17">During the probationary period, either of the parties may terminate the employment relationship with a notice period of seven days; the first month of the employment relationship is deemed to be the probation period (Art. 335b(1), CO). Various provisions can be agreed in writing, by standard contract or collective agreement, though the probationary period may not exceed three months (Art. 335b.2 CO). In the event that a probation period is interrupted due to sickness, accident or the performance of a legal duty which is not voluntarily assumed, the probation period is prolonged correspondingly (Art. 335b(3), CO).</p>
			<p id="p18">A worker may terminate his/her employment contract with immediate effect for justifiable cause (Art. 337.1 CO) or in the event of insolvency of the employer, if the latter is unable to provide security for the worker's claims arising from the employment relationship (Art. 337a CO).</p>
			<p id="p19">Workers may terminate the contract within the same timeframes as the employer, unless such termination is unreasonable or untimely. Resignation is untimely if the worker terminates the contract while a superior whom he/she is required to replace is performing a compulsory service (Art. 336d.1 CO).</p>
			<p id="p20">There is an abuse of rights if one of the parties terminates the employment contract (Art. 336. 1, CO):</p>
			<p id="p21">because of a quality inherent in the personality of the other party, unless such quality relates to the employment relationship or significantly impairs cooperation within the enterprise;</p>
			<p id="p22">because the other party exercises a constitutional right, unless the exercise of such right violates a duty of the employment relationship or significantly impairs cooperation within the enterprise;</p>
			<p id="p23">to solely frustrate the formation of claims of the other party arising out of the employment relationship;</p>
			<p id="p24">because the other party asserts in good faith claims arising out of the employment relationship;</p>
			<p id="p25">because the other party performs compulsory Swiss military service, civil defence service, military women’s service, or Red Cross service, or a legal duty not voluntarily assumed.</p>
			<p id="p26">Dismissal</p>
			<p id="p27">Two types of termination of employment relationship are envisaged under Swiss law. The employer may terminate the contract by ordinary dismissal or by means of dismissal with immediate effect. Justification is not required in the Swiss legal system for an ordinary dismissal, as dismissal with notice is not linked to the existence of a valid reason.</p>
			<p id="p28">The employer may at any time terminate the employment relationship without notice for valid reasons. A valid reason is considered to be any circumstance under which the terminating party can in good faith not be expected to continue the employment relationship (Art. 337(1), (2) and (3), CO).</p>
			<p id="p29">Upon expiry of the probation period, the employer may not terminate the employment relationship (Art. 336c(1), CO) during:</p>
			<p id="p30">the other party’s performance of compulsory Swiss military service, civil defence, women’s military service, or Red Cross service and, in case such service lasts more than 11 days, during the four weeks prior to and after the service;</p>
			<p id="p31">the period that the worker is prevented from performing his or her work fully or partially by no fault of his or her own due to sickness or accident for 30 days in the first year of service, for 90 days as of the second year of service until and within the fifth year of service, and for 180 days as of the sixth year of service;</p>
			<p id="p32">pregnancy and during the 16 weeks following confinement; or</p>
			<p id="p33">the worker’s participation with the agreement of the employer in a foreign aid service assignment abroad ordered by the competent federal agency.</p>
			<p id="p34">Collective dismissals are those made by the employer within a period of 30 days for reasons which are not related to the personality of the workers and affecting the following numbers of workers (sec. 335d, CO):</p>
			<p id="p35">ten workers in establishments employing between 20 and 100 workers;</p>
			<p id="p36">10 per cent of the workforce in establishments employing between 100 and 300 workers; and</p>
			<p id="p37">30 workers in establishments employing more than 300 workers.</p>
			<p id="p38">There is an abuse of rights if the employer dismisses the worker (Art. 336. 2, CO):</p>
			<p id="p39">because the worker belongs or does not belong to an employee association, or because he or she lawfully exercises a union activity;</p>
			<p id="p40">during the period the worker is an elected employee representative in a company institution or in an enterprise affiliated thereto, provided that the employer cannot prove a justified motive for the termination (note that the protection of the worker representative whose term of office has ended because of a transfer of employment relationships remains in effect up to the moment when this term would have expired if the transfer did not take place); or</p>
			<p id="p41">without respecting the consultation procedure prescribed for collective dismissals.</p>
			<p id="p42">Notice and prior procedural safeguards</p>
			<p id="p43">Upon the request of the other party, the party giving notice has to state the reason for terminating the employment contract (Art. 335, CO).</p>
			<p id="p44">The ordinary period of dismissal notice varies according to length of service. The notice period is of one month during the first year of service, two months for the employment lasting two to nine years, and three months for the employment whose duration exceeds nine years. The timeframes envisaged under the law may be changed by written agreement, standard employment contract or collective agreement, but may not be less than one month. Exceptions to this rule are admitted during the first year and if they have been set by a collective agreement (Art. 335c CO).</p>
			<p id="p45">An employment relationship for a fixed period of time ends without notice of termination. If such a relationship is tacitly continued after the expiration of the agreed period, it is deemed to be an indefinite employment relationship. After ten years, either of the parties may terminate a fixed-term employment relationship which has been entered into for a longer period with a notice period of six months (Art. 334(1), (2) and (3), CO).</p>
			<p id="p46">In the case of collective redundancies, the employer may terminate the employment contracts with a 30-day notice period (Art. 335d CO). The employer is also required to consult the workers' representatives before proceeding to redundancies and allow them to formulate proposals on the means of averting collective dismissals or to limit the number of persons affected and minimize the consequences. The employer must state in writing the reasons for dismissal, the number of workers affected, the number of workers regularly employed and the period in which the dismissals are to take place. He or she must send a copy of this statement to the Cantonal Labour Office, which will try to find solutions to the problems posed by the collective dismissals. The workers’ representatives may submit their observations (Art. 335f and g, CO).</p>
			<p id="p47">Notice given during the periods stated in sec. 336c(1), CO, is deemed void (see above). If the notice is given prior to the beginning of such period, the expiry will be suspended and will continue only after termination of the final period (sec. 336c(2)).</p>
			<p id="p48">The national CCE concerning hotels, restaurants and cafés (CCE for 1996) prescribes notice periods which are shorter than those contained in the CO (a month for the completion of between one month and five years of service, and two months after the fifth year of service).</p>
			<p id="p49">Severance pay</p>
			<p id="p50">Upon termination of the employment relationship of a worker of at least 50 years of age and with 20 or more years of service, the employer has to pay the worker a severance allowance, the amount of which may be fixed by written agreement, standard employment contract or collective employment contract, but it should not be less than an amount equal to the worker’s wages for two months (Arts. 339b and 339c, CO).</p>
			<p id="p51">If the amount of the severance pay is not fixed, a judge may set it at his or her discretion, but it should not exceed the amount equal to the worker’s wages for eight months.</p>
			<p id="p52">Severance pay may be reduced or eliminated if the employment relationship was terminated by the employee without a valid reason or by the employer with a valid reason. Collective employment contracts may contain additional provisions in this regard.</p>
			<p id="p53">Avenues for redress</p>
			<p id="p54">If the termination is unreasonable or if termination with immediate effect is not based on justifiable cause, the party concerned is entitled to compensation (Art. 336a.1, 337d.1 CO).</p>
			<p id="p55">The employer and worker may terminate an employment contract immediately and without notice, if there are good grounds for such immediate termination, especially in circumstances which, in keeping with the rules of good faith, render the continuation of the work relationship intolerable for said people (Art. 337 CO). If termination with immediate effect is unjustified, it does nonetheless remain valid. However, the party who terminates the contract with immediate effect without justifiable cause must indemnify the other party.</p>
			<p id="p56">The party who improperly gives notice of termination of the employment relationship must pay the other party compensation in an amount to be determined by the presiding judge. However, such compensation must not exceed an amount corresponding to the worker’s wages for six months. Claims for damages based on other legal grounds are unaffected. There are no provisions for reinstatement (Arts. 336a(1), (2) and (3), CO).</p>
			<p id="p57">If the employer dismisses the worker without notice in the absence of a valid reason, the latter will have a claim for compensation of what he or she would have earned if the employment relationship had been terminated by observing the notice period or until the expiry of any applicable fixed-term period. Offset against this compensation will be any amount the worker saved because of the termination of employment relationship, or any amount he or she earned from other work, or which he or she intentionally failed to earn. The presiding judge may order the employer to pay an indemnity to the worker which the judge may determine at his or her discretion, taking into account all circumstances. Such indemnity may not, however, exceed the worker’s wages for six months (Art. 337c, CO).</p>
			<p id="p58">The employment relationship ends 30 days after the notification of collective dismissal to the Cantonal Labour Office. Dismissal is considered abusive if the employer has not respected the consultation procedure prescribed for collective dismissals. If this is the case, compensation corresponding to the employee’s wages for a period of up to two months will be due. However, an applicable CCE may contain provisions for the payment of additional compensation (Arts. 336c(2) and 336a(3), CO).</p>
			<p id="p59">If a worker wishes to claim compensation, he or she must file a written objection against the termination with the party who gave notice of termination no later than by the end of the notice period. If the objection is validly made, and if the parties cannot agree on a continuation of the employment relationship, the party who has received notice of termination may assert his or her claim for compensation. The claim is forfeited if no legal action is taken within 180 days after the employment relationship has ended (Art. 336b(1) and (2), CO).</p>
			<p id="p60">The procedure is conducted at the cantonal level, and such cases are usually heard by a civil court. Some cantons have established labour courts. The cantons are required to provide a simple and rapid procedure for dealing with all claims brought relating to employment contracts and involving sums under 30,000 Swiss francs (Art. 343, CO).</p>
			<p id="p61">The burden of proof lies with the employer in two following cases: discriminating dismissal of a women and dismissal of a workers’ representative. In all the other cases, the worker dismissed has to prove that the employer has violated the provisions of the Swiss legislation.</p>
			<p id="p62">Further information</p>
			<p id="p63">Employment protection legislation database - EPLex</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>