<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Country Summary: Venezuela - Termination of Employment - Information Resources - Social Dialogue, Labour Law and Labour Administration Department</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Country Summary: Venezuela - Termination of Employment - Information Resources - Social Dialogue, Labour Law and Labour Administration Department</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-20 10:40:19.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://www.ilo.org/public/english/dialogue/ifpdial/info/termination/countries/venezuela.htm</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>ILO</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>OIT</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>BIT</keyTerm>
					<keyTerm>International Labour Organization</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/LAB_EN/232.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Information last updated 2000.</p>
			<p id="p2">Sources of regulation</p>
			<p id="p3">Art. 88 of the Venezuelan Constitution [1] states that “the law shall adopt measures intended to guarantee stability of labour and shall establish the benefits to compensate for seniority of service of a worker and protect him in case of unemployment”.</p>
			<p id="p4">The primary source relating to labour is the Basic Labour Act (BLA) of 27 November 1990. [2] Collective agreements are another source of law which often encompass termination of employment, making particular reference to dismissal for invalid reasons, procedures and benefits. In practice, tripartite commissions established through agreements place high priority on problems linked to dismissal. The case law of labour courts and decisions of the labour inspectorate (and decisions to settle legal disputes) supplement these sources of regulation, particularly in the area of immunities.</p>
			<p id="p5">Scope of legislation</p>
			<p id="p6">Career officials and white-collar employees in public service at the national, state or municipal levels are not covered by the provisions of the BLA in so far as they are governed by the administrative career regulations. Nevertheless, in any matter not so regulated they may enjoy benefits through labour legislation applicable to workers in the private sector. Members of the armed forces and state security corps are also excluded from the scope of this legislation (secs. 7 and 8, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p7">All enterprises, establishments, undertakings and businesses, whether state-owned, in existence or yet to be founded in Venezuela, and in general any performance of personal service involving employers and workers in any form whatsoever, are subject to the provisions of the BLA, the sole exceptions being those explicitly mentioned in the Act (sec. 15, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p8">Apprentices, young persons, domestic workers, caretakers, home workers, professional sports people, rural workers, persons employed in land, air and inland water transport, seafarers, motorized workers, actors, musicians, folklorists and other intellectual and cultural workers and disabled persons are covered by special conditions (Title V, Special Conditions, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p9">Contracts of employment</p>
			<p id="p10">Pursuant to sec. 67 of the BLA, an employment contract is one whereby a person undertakes to render services to another, under the control of the latter and in return for remuneration. </p>
			<p id="p11">There are no statutory provisions for probation periods. There is a trial period of 90 days for workers assigned to a higher post, although this can in no way be construed as constituting indirect dismissal (sec. 103(2), BLA).</p>
			<p id="p12">In principle, a contract is deemed to be of indeterminate duration if the parties do not explicitly state the desire to be bound by an employment relationship solely for a specified task or for a specified period (sec. 72 et seq., BLA). The following three conditions govern the conclusion of contracts for a specified period:</p>
			<p id="p13">for a contract for a specified period, blue-collar workers, one year maximum;</p>
			<p id="p14">for a contract for a specified period, white-collar workers, three years maximum; and</p>
			<p id="p15">for a contract for a specified task, the time necessary for its performance.</p>
			<p id="p16">In the first two cases, contracts may be concluded only when the nature of the service warrants it, for example, the provisional and legitimate replacement of a worker and when Venezuelan workers conclude contracts to work outside the country. An extension may be granted, although in the case of two or more extensions the contract is considered to be of indeterminate duration. The contract is also deemed of indeterminate duration if, within a month of its expiry, a new contract is concluded between the same parties, unless the parties clearly demonstrate their mutual wish to end the relationship.</p>
			<p id="p17">If, within a month of the termination of a contract for a particular task, the parties conclude a new contract for the performance of another task, it will be understood that they were bound from the outset of the relationship for an indeterminate period.</p>
			<p id="p18">Termination of employment</p>
			<p id="p19">Employment may be terminated, under sec. 98 of the BLA, other than at the initiative of the employer, by mutual agreement by the parties, for reasons foreign to the wishes of both, [3] and on the resignation of the worker.</p>
			<p id="p20">Resignation is the unilateral termination of the employment relationship by the worker. The BLA does not impose an obligation on the worker to submit written notice of resignation stating the reason, if any, for such action. Indeed, the BLA provides for termination of employment by the worker without reason and requires only the submission of notice ranging from seven to 30 days, depending on the worker’s length of service (after a month, seven days; after six months, 15 days; and after one year, 30 days). In lieu of notice, in the case of contracts of indeterminate duration, the worker must indemnify the employer by payment of a sum corresponding to the wages he or she would have earned during the notice period (sec. 107, BLA). In the case of contracts for a specified period or task, the judge may order a worker to pay as compensation for damages an amount which must not exceed one-half of the remuneration which would have been due up to the completion of the task or service (sec. 110, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p21">However, if resignation is for a justified reason, there is a 30-day period in which the worker may invoke the right to resign (sec. 101, BLA). Resignation is considered justified when it is based on a reason prescribed by statute and its financial effects are equivalent to those of unjustified dismissal (see below). Dishonesty, immoral actions with regard to the worker or his or her family, insult or serious lack of respect towards the worker or his or her family, forgetfulness which jeopardizes safety or health in the workplace, serious breach of the obligations under the contract of employment, and any act amounting to indirect dismissal (secs. 100 and 103, BLA) constitute just cause for resignation. </p>
			<p id="p22">Dismissal is indirect when an employer who wishes to terminate employment uses indirect means to induce the worker to resign, and gives cause for justified resignation. Indirect dismissal is also considered by law to cover the following cases (sec. 103(1), BLA):</p>
			<p id="p23">if a worker is required to do work which is distinct from that for which he or she was engaged, or which is incompatible with the worker’s dignity or qualifications;</p>
			<p id="p24">if a worker is required to perform services which occasion a change of residence which was not stipulated in the contract or implied in the nature of the work;</p>
			<p id="p25">if remuneration or grade of the worker’s post are lowered; or</p>
			<p id="p26">if working hours are arbitrarily changed or any similar actions are taken.</p>
			<p id="p27">Dismissal</p>
			<p id="p28">According to Venezuelan law, dismissal is the manifestation of the employer’s desire to end the employment relationship (sec. 99, BLA). Dismissal is unjustified when the worker has committed no action to justify it. Such justification must be claimed within 30 consecutive days after the date on which the worker is informed, or should have been informed, of the facts constituting grounds for the unilateral termination of employment by the employer (sec. 101, BLA). This also applies to reasons relating to the operational requirements of the undertaking such as collective dismissal and staff reduction without prior notification. Mass dismissal is classified as the loss of employment by 10 per cent of the workers in an enterprise employing more than 100 persons, 20 per cent of more than 50 workers, or ten workers in an undertaking employing fewer than 50 workers, within a period of three months (sec. 34, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p29">The contract of employment may be terminated for (sec. 102, BLA):</p>
			<p id="p30">dishonesty or immoral behaviour;</p>
			<p id="p31">acts of violence except in legitimate self-defence;</p>
			<p id="p32">insult or serious lack of respect towards the employer, his or her representatives or family members living in his or her home;</p>
			<p id="p33">deliberate action or a gross negligent act affecting safety or health in the workplace;</p>
			<p id="p34">forgetfulness or carelessness seriously affecting safety or health in the workplace;</p>
			<p id="p35">unjustified absence from work for three working days within the period of one month;</p>
			<p id="p36">material damage to the plant, tools, furniture belonging to the enterprise, raw materials, finished or partly processed products, plantations or other relevant property, whether deliberate or resulting from serious negligence;</p>
			<p id="p37">disclosure of secrets of production, construction or process;</p>
			<p id="p38">serious breach of the obligations under the contract of employment; or</p>
			<p id="p39">abandonment of work, which is defined as:</p>
			<p id="p40">leaving the workplace inopportunely or without valid reason during working hours, without authorization from the employer or his or her representative;</p>
			<p id="p41">refusal to perform the assigned tasks under the agreed terms of the labour contract or legislation. However, the refusal to undertake work which might create an imminent or serious hazard to the life or health of the worker is not considered abandonment; or</p>
			<p id="p42">unjustified absence by a worker responsible for a process or machine when such absence entails disruption in the rest of the service or production process.</p>
			<p id="p43">Venezuelan law provides that certain workers, for various reasons, are irremovable and may not be dismissed, transferred or employed in less favourable working conditions without just cause approved in advance by the labour inspector (sec. 449, BLA). This protection is, generally, reserved for trade union promoters and board members, promoters of collective agreements and workers involved in collective disputes against employers, but has also been extended to other categories of persons, whether or not they are linked to trade union activity or collective relations. The following may therefore enjoy protection under the BLA:</p>
			<p id="p44">a worker who has been suspended from work (sec. 94);</p>
			<p id="p45">a pregnant woman, during pregnancy and up to one year after confinement (sec. 384);</p>
			<p id="p46">an adoptive mother, during the year following adoption (sec. 384(1));</p>
			<p id="p47">board members of a trade union, during their management and up to three months after the expiry of the term for which they were elected (sec. 451);</p>
			<p id="p48">promoters (and applicants for memberships), from the date of notification until registration of the union, which should not exceed three months (sec. 450);</p>
			<p id="p49">the trade union delegate aboard a ship flying the Venezuelan flag (sec. 356);</p>
			<p id="p50">workers during trade union elections, from the notice of convocation until the election itself, a period which should not exceed three months within a period of two years (sec. 452);</p>
			<p id="p51">workers involved in a collective labour dispute (secs. 458 and 506);</p>
			<p id="p52">workers affected by a draft collective agreement, during the period of negotiations and up to 180 days, which may be extended by 90 days in exceptional circumstances (secs. 458 and 520);</p>
			<p id="p53">workers who accept changes in working conditions for economic reasons which jeopardize the work or existence of the enterprise, during the period the agreement is in force (secs. 525 and 526);</p>
			<p id="p54">workers affected by the request procedure of the standard-setting labour meetings, during the meeting session (secs. 528 and 533(f));</p>
			<p id="p55">workers who are appointed labour directors or substitutes during their terms in office (sec. 617); and</p>
			<p id="p56">members of the safety and health committee of the enterprise while they are exercising their functions on the committee (sec. 37). [4]</p>
			<p id="p57">Notice and prior procedural safeguards</p>
			<p id="p58">Notice of dismissal must be made in writing and state the reason on which it is based. An employer is not permitted to subsequently rely on a reason for dismissal that is not specified in the notice. Where a dismissal has been issued orally, the absence of a written document does not prevent an employee who wished to challenge his or her dismissal from using other evidence to prove that he or she has been dismissed (sec. 195, BLA). Furthermore, the employer is required to inform the district labour-stability judge of the dismissal, stating the reasons justifying his or her action within five working days. Failure to do so will be interpreted as the employer’s acknowledgement of lack of justification for the dismissal (sec. 116, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p59">Notice in the case of unjustified dismissal must be conveyed in advance according to the following schedule (sec. 104, BLA):</p>
			<p id="p60">after one month’s service, one week;</p>
			<p id="p61">after six months’ service, two weeks;</p>
			<p id="p62">after one year’s service, one month;</p>
			<p id="p63">after five years’ service, two months; and</p>
			<p id="p64">after ten years’ service, three months.</p>
			<p id="p65">In lieu of notice, the worker should be paid a sum equivalent to the remuneration he or she would have received during the corresponding period (sec. 106, BLA). In addition, a worker will receive compensation in lieu of notice as follows (sec. 104, BLA):</p>
			<p id="p66">15 days’ wages when the period of service is more than one month but six months or less;</p>
			<p id="p67">30 days’ wages when it is more than six months but less than one year;</p>
			<p id="p68">45 days’ wages when it is one year or more;</p>
			<p id="p69">60 days’ wages when it is two years or more but less than ten years; and</p>
			<p id="p70">90 days’ wages when it is ten years or more.</p>
			<p id="p71">The Ministry of Labour may suspend collective dismissals, for social reasons, by a special ruling and submit the dispute to arbitration if the parties cannot reach an agreement, or if reasons of an economic, technological or structural nature are invoked (sec. 34, BLA). The trade union to which the workers belong or, in the absence of a trade union, the workers themselves must be notified of the employer’s application. There are no express provisions for compensation in this case. The worker is entitled to a period of notice, as follows (sec 104, BLA):</p>
			<p id="p72">after one month’s service, one week in advance;</p>
			<p id="p73">after six months’ service, two weeks in advance;</p>
			<p id="p74">after one year’s service, one month in advance;</p>
			<p id="p75">after five years’ service, two months in advance; and</p>
			<p id="p76">after ten years’ service, three months in advance.</p>
			<p id="p77">In lieu of notice, the worker may be compensated with a sum equivalent to the remuneration he or she would have received during the corresponding period (sec. 106, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p78">Legislation (sec. 453, BLA) lays down an administrative procedure for requests submitted by the employer to dismiss, transfer or justifiably lower the working conditions of the worker enjoying trade union immunity. Similarly, a statutory provision provides (sec. 454, BLA) for these workers the procedure of reinstatement (reenganche) in the event that the employer may have dismissed, transferred or lowered the working conditions of a worker without fulfilling the above-mentioned requirements.</p>
			<p id="p79">Severance pay</p>
			<p id="p80">In the case of unjustified dismissal in contracts for a specified task or service, the employer is obliged to pay compensation for damages in an amount equal to that of the remuneration which would have been due up to the completion of the task or expiry of the period (sec. 110, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p81">If the employer insists on dismissing the worker he or she must pay, in addition to the salaries which the worker would have earned during the legal proceedings, compensation amounting to ten days’ wages if the employee’s length of service is between three and six months; 30 days’ wages if the length of service is six months or more, and then 30 days’ wages for each year of service, up to a maximum of 150 days’ wages (sec. 125, BLA). Moreover, the employer may, upon dismissal, double the severance allowance and thereby avoid legal proceedings for reinstatement mentioned below and the payment of wages accrued during the course of such proceedings (sec. 126, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p82">In accordance with the 1997 revision of the law, the worker has the right to a seniority bonus that accrues interest and that is to be paid monthly or upon termination of the employment relationship at the worker’s initiative (sec. 108, BLA). This is the equivalent of:</p>
			<p id="p83">after three months of service, five days’ wages;</p>
			<p id="p84">after the second year of service, an additional two days’ wages per year of service, up to a maximum of 30 years.</p>
			<p id="p85">When the employment relationship ends, the worker has a right to a seniority benefit, up to 75 per cent of which can be payable in advance. The amount is:</p>
			<p id="p86">15 days’ wages or, if monthly contributions or deposits have been made, the proportion of this amount remaining to be paid, when the period of service is between three and six months;</p>
			<p id="p87">the difference between the amount contributed or deposited monthly and 45 days’ wages when the period of service is more than six months but less than one year; or</p>
			<p id="p88">the difference between the amount contributed or deposited monthly in the year in which the employment relationship ended and 60 days’ wages, after the first year of service, and provided the worker has been working for more than six months of the relevant year.</p>
			<p id="p89">Bankruptcy is one of the hypothetical reasons for the termination of employment and in such cases the rights derived from the relationship of employment are preferential. Payments to workers are handled independently of bankruptcy proceedings by creditors. The amount of compensation varies depending on whether the bankruptcy was fraudulent or fortuitous. If bankruptcy is deemed to be caused by third parties or through negligence, the worker has the right to double compensation, whereas if bankruptcy has resulted from unforeseen or inevitable events it is considered fortuitous.</p>
			<p id="p90">Avenues for redress</p>
			<p id="p91">Reinstatement of the worker represents an option between admission to employment and compensation by the employer.</p>
			<p id="p92">Depending on the circumstances and nature of the termination, the presiding judge may rule that the worker should be reinstated and back wages paid. Rehiring is also an option for the employer (secs. 125 and 126, BLA). However, temporary, provisional, occasional and domestic workers are not entitled to reinstatement. Likewise, employers who regularly employ fewer than ten persons are not obliged to reinstate dismissed workers (secs. 112 and 117, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p93">Once the type of dismissal has been established, the judge must give notice to the employer to submit his or her rebuttal within five working days, initiating a probation period of eight working days, unless the judge deems it unnecessary. When this period has expired, the judge must pronounce a verdict on the justification or inadmissibility of the dismissal in a time limit not exceeding 15 working days, provided that a request has not been made for the constitution of a tribunal to pronounce a verdict (secs. 117, 118 and 119, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p94">Appeals against the verdict may be lodged with the Higher Labour Tribunal which will decide on the substance of the dispute and confirm or reject the plea for reinstatement and payment of forfeited wages. No appeal is allowed to the court of cassation against a decision of this Tribunal (secs. 121, 122 and 123, BLA).</p>
			<p id="p95">Further information</p>
			<p id="p96">[1] 1961 Constitution, amended in 1979 and 1983.</p>
			<p id="p97">[2] Rules relating to remuneration and dismissal were amended in 1997 as a result of a tripartite agreement in April of that year.</p>
			<p id="p98">[3] For example, death or incapacity of the worker which makes it impossible for him or her to continue rendering his or her services and force majeure in case of plant closure or fortuitous bankruptcy.</p>
			<p id="p99">[4] Basic Act on prevention, working conditions and the working environment.</p>
			<p id="p100">Employment protection legislation database - EPLex</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>