<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<cesDoc version="0.4">
	<cesHeader version="0.4">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>bt - Full Story</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>
						<type>Crawling and normalization</type>
						<name>ILSP</name>
					</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Panacea project</distributor>
				<eAddress type="web">http://www.panacea-lr.eu</eAddress>
				<availability>Under review</availability>
				<pubDate>2012</pubDate>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>bt - Full Story</title>
						<author></author>
						<imprint>
							<publisher></publisher>
							<pubDate>2010-09-20 10:37:10.0</pubDate>
							<eAddress>http://www.businesstodayegypt.com/article.aspx?ArticleID=6075</eAddress>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language iso639="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<keyTerm>Egypt; Egyptian; business; Sherine Bakir; labor law; employment; hiring firing human resources; Menha Samy Ibrachy &amp; Demarkar; Social Insurance Office; Khaled Kamel Henkel; FAQ</keyTerm>
				</keywords>
				<domain></domain>
				<subdomain/>
				<subject/>
			</textClass>
			<annotations>
				<annotation>http://sifnos.ilsp.gr/panacea/D4.3/data/20101230/LAB_EN/28.html</annotation>
			</annotations>
		</profileDesc>
	</cesHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<p id="p1">Don’t take that two-day weekend for granted: six working days a week are standard by law.</p>
			<p id="p2">In The Black</p>
			<p id="p3">By Ashraf Talaat</p>
			<p id="p4">By Khaled Habib</p>
			<p id="p5">To contest a wrongful termination, an employee must first register a complaint with the State Labor Office.</p>
			<p id="p6">By Omar Mohsen</p>
			<p id="p7">November 2005</p>
			<p id="p8">A Constant Pull</p>
			<p id="p9">The nearly two-year-old labor law has managed to release employers and employees alike from several constraints in the old tug of war between benefits, wages and flexibility, but companies still must mind a broad slate of their workers’ rights</p>
			<p id="p10">By Sherine Bakir</p>
			<p id="p11">In the ailing economic conditions of the late 1990s and early part of this decade, employers and employees alike were burdened with the intractable battle of trying to make ends meet. Amid skyrocketing unemployment rates, the government decided it was time to organize the employment process and pass a new labor law that could better govern the relationship between privately owned companies and their employees.</p>
			<p id="p12">In July 2003, the new labor law (Law 12 of 2003) went into effect with the stated goal of fostering an atmosphere that would support and move forward the privatization process. Although the law reorganized the procedures under which a private corporation can hire or fire its employees, it was far from perfect: the nation is still high on the World Bank’s Rigidity of Employment index for the strength of its work contracts and stringent barriers to their termination even in cases of bankruptcy.</p>
			<p id="p13">“Egypt’s labor law has to not only protect, but also loosen the grip on both parties involved in the employment process,” says Menha Samy, an associate at Ibrachy &amp; Dermarkar, a leading Egyptian law office. “In the end, employers and employees alike want to earn money, so the law has to help employers better run their businesses.”</p>
			<p id="p14">To better understand the current parameters and issues in the law, take a look at bt’s brief FAQ.</p>
			<p id="p15">What are the main conditions an employer has to abide by when hiring an employee?</p>
			<p id="p16">After settling on hiring conditions, the employer and employee must compose a legally binding labor contract, which the employer puts on file with the employee’s resume stating the new hire’s date of birth, profession, qualifications and previous experience. The contract must be written in Arabic and produced in triplicate for employer, employee and the Social Insurance Office’s registry.</p>
			<p id="p17">In addition to standard identification information, the contract must explicitly include the following information: a comprehensive job description, the wage agreed upon, the method of payment and the probation period, which should not exceed three months.</p>
			<p id="p18">Are there different types of labor contracts?</p>
			<p id="p19">There are two types of labor contracts: temporary and permanent contracts. Temporary contracts are time-limited documents under which an employee is hired for a specific period of time, usually for a year or two. Employers can renew the contract before it lapses only if they denote that in the contract.</p>
			<p id="p20">“However, if the employer does not specify the possibility of renewal in the contract and fails to renew or terminate the contract before the last day of expiry, then the contract gets automatically renewed to a permanent one,” says Samy.</p>
			<p id="p21">A permanent contract is an open-ended contract that involves hiring an employee without constraints on how long he or she will hold that position and termination becomes much more difficult. Permanent contracts can only be terminated on the condition of notifying the other party in writing at least two months before termination.</p>
			<p id="p22">If the employee is being bought out, he or she is entitled to a severance package at the rate of a half-month’s salary for each of the first five years plus one month’s salary for every year thereafter.</p>
			<p id="p23">If the employer is the one terminating the contract, then the employee has the right to have one paid day off per week during this two-month notice period to look for another job.</p>
			<p id="p24">Resignations must be submitted in writing, and the employee has the right to withdraw the resignation within a week of its acceptance.</p>
			<p id="p25">How long can employees legally work? How costly are overtime work hours?</p>
			<p id="p26">The standard legal work schedule is eight hours per day, six days per week. Work days must include at least one break of not less than one hour for meals and rest. Employees are also granted a minimum of 24 unbroken hours of rest per week.</p>
			<p id="p27">In other words: private sector employees on a five-day workweek, thank your employers. They are giving you 52 free days of unpaid leave every year.</p>
			<p id="p28">If the employee has worked in excess of 8 hours a day, he or she is entitled to a 35% premium for daytime hours and 70% extra for nighttime hours. Moreover, if the employee has to work during his day of rest, then his or her wage is doubled during that day.</p>
			<p id="p29">The law stipulates that no employee should work more than 10 hours (work hours plus overtime) in any 24-hour period.</p>
			<p id="p30">“The work hours stipulated under the law are not sufficient for our factory needs,” says Khaled Kamel, Henkel’s administrative manager. “We often need our workers to work 12 hours per day to meet our production needs, or else costs become very high.”</p>
			<p id="p31">How is an employee’s salary computed?</p>
			<p id="p32">According to Article 34 of the law, a National Council for Wages has been established under the auspices of the Minister of Planning to determine minimum wages at a level reflective of the cost of living to balance between salaries and prices.</p>
			<p id="p33">The council has yet to set a minimum salary, be it hourly, daily, weekly or monthly.</p>
			<p id="p34">The US Department of Labor reported in 1999 that Egypt’s minimum wage had been LE 116 per month under the old law (recent inflation due to 2003’s pound float has made this salary much less livable). The reinstatement of a minimum wage would significantly change current employment practices.</p>
			<p id="p35">The council, however, has ruled that minimum annual raises should not be less than 7% of an employee’s base salary, thanks to the new tax law.</p>
			<p id="p36">The law also prohibits favoritism in salaries because of the sex, origin, language or religious beliefs of employees. Salaries are either determined according to labor contracts or the statute of the corporation.</p>
			<p id="p37">Otherwise, an employee will be entitled to a salary equivalent to that of a colleague of the same rank.</p>
			<p id="p38">Employees may also be paid on a commission basis provided there is a minimum guaranteed wage.</p>
			<p id="p39">How much vacation is the average employee entitled to?</p>
			<p id="p40">It depends on how long the person has been employed. Article 47 of the law stipulates that employees who have completed one year on the job have the right to 21 working days of annual leave, including at least six continuous days. The vacation is increased to a period of 30 days per year once the employee spends ten or more years on the job. Employees over the age of 50 are also entitled to 30 working days of annual leave, regardless of how long they have been with the company.</p>
			<p id="p41">“One of the main amendments of the law is that weekends as well as national and religious holidays [13 days per year] are no longer included in the vacation period,” says Samy.</p>
			<p id="p42">Newly hired employees who have served for a period less than one year but more than six months are entitled to a vacation in proportion with the period spent at work. “That is to say, those who have worked for six months can have an average of a two-week vacation,” explains Samy.</p>
			<p id="p43">The employer can prevent an employee from taking vacation in a time of high or urgent work, except when the employee has to sit for an exam, provided that he or she has notified the employer at least 15 days before the exam is scheduled to take place.</p>
			<p id="p44">The employer has the right not to pay an employee’s salary if he or she worked for another corporation while on vacation leave.</p>
			<p id="p45">“We give a priority to our business and production needs when an employee requests a vacation; however, it is not a trend to reject a request,” says Henkel’s Kamel. “We also pay employees who do not take leave during [our busiest] month an extra LE 100 as an incentive.”</p>
			<p id="p46">What are the different types of vacation periods besides annual leave?</p>
			<p id="p47">Casual leave: The employee has the right to abstain from work for a period not exceeding six days per year with a maximum of two consecutive days each time. Casual leave is considered a part of the employee’s annual vacation.</p>
			<p id="p48">Pilgrimage leave: An employee who has spent five continuous years on a job is entitled to a fully paid one-month vacation, once during the employee’s career, for the performance of the holy pilgrimage either to Saudi Arabia (Muslims) or Jerusalem (Copts).</p>
			<p id="p49">“Resolving disputes in court is a very complicated thing to do. In reality it is very tough to bring together three judges in one committee — now imagine five.”</p>
			<p id="p50">Sick leave: To be entitled to sick leave, the employee must first present a medical certificate accredited by an official medical clinic. The Social Insurance Law determines the employee’s salary compensation during the sick leave period. The employee has the right to a sick leave every three years, during which he or she will receive a full salary for a one-month leave followed by 75% of the salary for eight months and then leave without pay. The employee may also request transferring the sick leave into annual leave if s/he has a sufficient balance.</p>
			<p id="p51">Maternity leave: The law permits a female employee to take paid maternity leave twice during her entire career provided that she has completed ten months of employment. Under the law, women are entitled to 90 fully paid days of maternity leave.</p>
			<p id="p52">An employer does not have the right to force a female employee to work during the first 45 days following the delivery. Furthermore, an employer is prohibited from discharging a female employee or terminating her contract during her maternity leave, giving her more job security. Female employees also have the right to take a further two years unpaid leave twice during their career with a company without any threat to their job security.</p>
			<p id="p53">Men are not eligible for paternity leave.</p>
			<p id="p54">What is considered inappropriate conduct for an employee?</p>
			<p id="p55">Article 57 of the law clearly states unacceptable acts in which an employee should not engage. They are as follows: Keeping original copies of any document related to work; working for a third party, with or without pay, if it adversely affects the performance and quality of his/her work; engaging in an activity similar to that of the employer’s during the period of the contract; borrowing money from clients; accepting gifts, money or commissions for any transaction or duty; and collecting donations, fundraising or solicit signatures without the prior consent of the employer.</p>
			<p id="p56">What kind of penalties will the employee face in case of violating work policies?</p>
			<p id="p57">If an employee is in violation of any of the corporation’s statutes or policies, the following disciplinary sanctions may be imposed, one at a time: Warning letters; fines (up to 5 days of salary); postponement of annual raise (for up to three months); reduction of annual raise by up to 50%; postponement of promotion for a period not exceeding one year; Reduction of base salary by an amount equal to the last raise received; demoting the employee to a lower rank without a reduction in salary; termination, according to the provisions of the law.</p>
			<p id="p58">These sanctions can only be imposed on the employee after notifying him/her in writing of the infraction and conducting an investigation within seven days of discovering the infraction to hear the employee’s statement and defense. The number of warning letters necessary during the course of the investigation depends on the seriousness of the infraction, according to Samy.</p>
			<p id="p59">Either the employer or the corporation’s legal department can conduct the investigation. The employer has the right to provisionally suspend the employee during the investigation for a period not exceeding 60 days while paying his/her full salary.</p>
			<p id="p60">“We often send a warning letter at first, and upon reoccurrence of the same conduct, we resort to firing the employee,” says Kamel.</p>
			<p id="p61">Moreover, the law states clearly in Article 67, “If the employee is charged with committing a crime, a misdemeanor of moral turpitude, or breach of honor, the employer may provisionally suspend him/her from work and raise the matter to a specialized committee within three days from the date of suspension.”</p>
			<p id="p62">If the committee approves of the suspension, the employee will be paid half his salary, but in case of rejection of the suspension, the employee will receive the salary paid in full from the date of suspension.</p>
			<p id="p63">What are the offences for which an employer can fire an employee?</p>
			<p id="p64">The law lists ‘grave errors’ that will result in the termination of the employee: Holding fake identity papers or submitting fraudulent documents; committing an error resulting in serious damages to the employer or corporation, provided that the employer notifies the authorities within 24 hours; violating the corporation’s regulations and policies posted in a visible spot and after a formal warning letter.</p>
			<p id="p65">Also grave: being absent without a legitimate justification for more than 20 intermittent days in the same year or for more than ten consecutive days, provided that a formal warning letter has been sent to the employee ten days after the final absence in the first case or five days in the second one; divulging the secrets of the corporation leading to the occurrence of severe damages; competing with the employer in the same field; and reporting to work in a state of plain drunkenness or under the influence of drugs; attacking employers or superiors during or because of work.</p>
			<p id="p66">“The absence case is the most common one in many corporations nowadays, and that is why it is phrased very clearly under the law,” Samy explains.</p>
			<p id="p67">How is an employer/employee dispute resolved?</p>
			<p id="p68">If an individual dispute arises between the employer and the employee, the State Labor Office first attempts to settle the dispute amicably.</p>
			<p id="p69">However, if no settlement is reached, both parties may resort to an arbitration committee to file a case within a period of 45 days at most. The committee must be composed of two judges, a representative of the Ministry of Manpower and Immigration, and two members of the Federation of Egyptian Trade Unions. The compensation determined by the committee should not be less than a two-month salary.</p>
			<p id="p70">“Such disputes usually take from two to four years to be resolved in court,” says Samy, adding that, “Resolving disputes in court is a very complicated and difficult thing to do. In reality, it is very tough to bring together three judges in one committee — now imagine five.”</p>
			<p id="p71">What will happen to employees if the corporation faces financial difficulties?</p>
			<p id="p72">The law makes it clear that an employer who faces harsh economic conditions during uncommon events like privatization or recession cannot dismiss any of its employees. Downsizing the corporation or merging it with another does not allow the company to terminate employment contracts, although it may reduce pay or modify the labor contract to include additional tasks.</p>
			<p id="p73">As for a company going out of business, the employer has the right to lay off his or her workers to eliminate all liabilities. The legal procedures necessary to do this are as follows: The employer has to justify to an ad hoc committee of government and union officials the reasons for taking such an action, as well as state the numbers and ranks of employees that need to be terminated. The employees have the right to object to any decisions taken by this committee, which will result in the formation of another ad hoc committee representing the employees. Both committees have to include representatives of the General Federation of Egyptian Trade Unions.</p>
			<p id="p74">The committees will try to balance between the interests of the corporation and those of the employees, taking into consideration the seniority, family burdens and vocational skills of employees.</p>
			<p id="p75">What is the legal retirement age?</p>
			<p id="p76">The official retirement age is 60 years old unless the employee is working under a temporary contract period that extends beyond his or her reaching that age. In that case, the contract terminates upon completion of the job.</p>
			<p id="p77">Employees receive their retirement fund and pension according to the Social Insurance Law, in addition to an indemnity at the rate of a half-month’s salary for each of the first five years and one month for each following year.</p>
			<p id="p78">Does the law grant employees the right to strike or object to certain work conditions?</p>
			<p id="p79">The law has granted employees the right to organize a strike, with no threat to their job security, under the supervision of their trade union organizations in defense of their vocational, economic and social interests.</p>
			<p id="p80">Trade unions are responsible for notifying employers of the date and the reason of the strike at least 10 days before it takes place. However, organizing strikes is prohibited if they result in any disturbance to national security or delay services provided to citizens.</p>
			<p id="p81">What is the status of non-Egyptian employees under the law?</p>
			<p id="p82">Foreigners working in Egypt have to present their legal work permits beforehand. The law also constrains the hiring of foreigners to a ratio of one foreigner to ten Egyptians, and all labor laws apply to Egyptians and foreigners equally.</p>
			<p id="p83">Foreigners also have to receive work licenses from the Labor Force Office, which requires them to undergo a security check; the prospective employer must also prove that the foreigner is more qualified to do that particular job than an Egyptian.</p>
			<p id="p84">What are the necessary steps an Egyptian must go through to be eligible to work abroad?</p>
			<p id="p85">In addition to gaining work permits from whatever country they end up working in, Egyptians seeking to work abroad also have to obtain a legal work permit from Egypt. They should also submit a description of the nature and requirements of their profession and copies of their labor contracts as well as state the negotiated salary.</p>
			<p id="p86">How does the law address the issue of gender discrimination?</p>
			<p id="p87">The law apparently does not tolerate gender discrimination as stated in Article 88: “All employment regulations and policies should apply to female employees equalizing their status to that of their male counterparts without discrimination as long as their work conditions are analogous.”</p>
			<p id="p88">What rights has the labor law guaranteed to Egyptian women?</p>
			<p id="p89">In addition to maternity leave, while breastfeeding, women are entitled to two break periods not less than half an hour each. “This means that a nursing mother can either arrive to work an hour late or leave an hour early,” Samy explains.</p>
			<p id="p90">The employer is required to establish day-care facilities for its employees if the corporation hires more than 100 female individuals. However, requiring employers to establish day-care facilities could be an unintentional drawback for women. “Establishing a day-care facility is by all means costly and hard to manage,” explains Kamel, a clause that led Henkel to only hire 50 women.</p>
			<p id="p91">Editor’s Note: This package was prepared in association with the law firm of Ibrachy &amp; Dermarkar and with a non-legally binding reading of the law and its executive regulations as provided by the Ministry of Manpower and Immigration. While we recognize the need for factual accuracy and have done everything reasonable within our power to make certain this package is both accurate and error-free, Business Today Egypt, its publisher and Ibrachy &amp; Dermarkar assume no liability or responsibility for any errors, omissions or inaccuracies contained in this story. Specific questions regarding issues of law should be referred to a competent professional using the Arabic text.</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</cesDoc>